<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The watering of the olive plant in Christs garden. Or A short catechism for the first entrance of our Chelmesford children: Enlarged by a three-fold appendix / by John Fisk ...</title>
            <author>Fiske, John, 1601-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09143</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W24610</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922708</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80922708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191876</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191876)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2893:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The watering of the olive plant in Christs garden. Or A short catechism for the first entrance of our Chelmesford children: Enlarged by a three-fold appendix / by John Fisk ...</title>
                  <author>Fiske, John, 1601-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green at Cambridg in New-England.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge, Mass.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Boston Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregational churches --  Catechisms --  English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> WATERING OF the OLIVE PLANT <hi>IN CHRISTS GARDEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR <hi>A SHORT CATECHISM</hi> For the firſt Entrance of our <hi>Chelmesford Children:</hi> Enlarged by <hi>A three-fold Appendix</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN FISK</hi> Paſtour of the Church of Chriſt at Chelmesford in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Thy Children ſhall be like Olive-plants round about thy Table. <bibl>Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 128. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Thoſe that be planted in the Houſe of the Lord ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of our God.</p>
               <p>They ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in old Age &amp;c:</p> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 92. 13, 14.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Samuel Green</hi> at CAMBRIDG in <hi>New-England.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:3"/>
            <head>To the Church &amp; Congregation at Chelmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Grace &amp; Peace, through Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>BEloved, What is here preſented to Publick view is yours: for looking to the poor-Penman, as Relating to you: to the external moving Cauſe, as ariſing firſtly &amp; freely from you, to the End &amp; uſe as centering in you, to the reaſon of the Publiſhing therof, as reſting with you, and the care &amp; coſts, as to that end expended by you: It muſt not otherwiſe be determined but YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RS. Which being ſo, you have ſaved me the labour, of prefacing on behalfe, either of this ſo neceſſary &amp; fruitfull an exerciſe of Catechiſing, or of this preſent draught: or of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing it. The preſent encumbrances of our new-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining you know to have declined me till of late, from the former, and mine own inabilities much more from the latter, as being rather deſirous to have made uſe of ſome others labours that way, or at leaſt-wiſe to have acted mine own feeble apprehenſions in a more private manner amongſt our ſelves. But God hath moved your minds, firſt to ſee, and ſeeing to cauſe, as it muſt be as it is. I ſhall add only a word or two touching uſe; 1. The Scripture quotations in the margent, are ſo ſevered by thoſe diſtinct marks as it is not hard to diſcern to which anſwer they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn 2. They are orderly ſet down (for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) as they relate to the ſeveral ſentences or part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
<pb facs="tcp:191876:4"/> in the anſwers. 3. Where more then one, are mentioned to the ſame purpoſe, it is not without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial cauſe, and may ſerve for help of memory, when we may have occaſion to branch out ſuch a ſubject, into its particulars. 4. profitably you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Promiſes to their proper heads in the Lords Prayer, and Dutyes or faylings to their proper places in the Decalogue. As for the annexing of theſe with the Doctrine of the Sacraments, by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix, It is becauſe the ſame will more ſuit with ſuch capacities as are allready entered, then ſuch as are but in their enterance. I ſay no more but this, If now you &amp; yours, (as is hoped) ſhall gain any Spiritual fruit by theſe poor weak Travells of mine, I have my deſire: and no ſmall encouragement, in the midst of many wilderneſs-diſcouragements. To His Bleſſing therefore I commit both you &amp; yours, who is the God of all Bleſſing: and Rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord John Fiske.</signed>
               <dateline>Chelmesford <date>this 25 of 1. <hi>mo:</hi> 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:191876:4"/>
            <head>THE OLIVE-PLANT WATERED.</head>
            <note place="margin">An Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</note>
            <p>Q. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO made thee, or gave</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>a</hi> Job 33. 4. Pſal. 100. 3. Iſay 45. 11. Acts 17. 28.</note> 
               <hi>thee thy Bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> GOD, the giver of Beings.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is GOD?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>b</hi> Nehe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9 6. Jer: 45. 12. &amp; 27. 5. Pro: 16. 4. 1 Cor: 8. 6. Exod: 20. 11</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Maker, Preſerver and Governour of all things.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are there not more Gods then one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, there is but One GOD in<note place="margin">
                  <hi>c</hi> 1 Cor: 8. 4, 6 Mat: 28. 19. 1 John 5. 7</note> three Perſons; the Father, Son, and Holy-Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherefore did He make, and doth He Preſerve thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal: 119. 37 Pſal. 100<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, 3. Joſh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. 16, 18, Iſay 1. 2.</note> Serve Him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How oughteſt thou to ſerve him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As <note n="e" place="margin">Iſay 8. 20. Deut: 10. 12. 13.</note> He hath appointed in his Law.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Which is his Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is breifly (<hi>f</hi>) contained in<note place="margin">Deut: 4. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat: 22. 40</note> the Ten Commandements.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhich are they?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 17, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. Mark 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſpake all theſe words &amp;c: as in Exod. 20.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Canſt thou keep this Law?</hi>
               <note place="margin">James<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. John 7. 19</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, (<hi>g</hi>) for in many things wee offend all.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What belongeth to the breach therof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="h" place="margin">Pro: 3. 33. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 3 10. Rom: 3. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> Curſe of God, and eternal damnation.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is then required to be known of thee that wouldeſt be ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. My <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rev: 3. 17. Mat: 9. 12.</note> miſery by nature. <hi>Eph 4. 18. Lam:</hi> 3. 39.</p>
            <p n="2">2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The means of my <note n="k" place="margin">Acts 2. 36. 37. Joh. 17. 3 Rev: 3. 18. 19</note> Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Recovery. <hi>Pſal. 49. 8. Gal. 4. 4, 5 Hoſea 13. 14. 1 Pet:</hi> 1. 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> My <note n="l" place="margin">Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 74 1 Tit: 2. 12. 1 Theſ. 2. 12.</note> Duty and thankfullnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired thereupon.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART 1.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>ARt thou then miſerable by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, in a <note n="m" place="margin">Rev: 3. 17 Rom: 3. 16</note> moſt miſerable condition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How, or in what reſpects?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> In reſpect of <note n="n" place="margin">Rom: 323. Rom: 5. 12.</note> Sin, and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:191876:5"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How in reſpect of Sin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that I am by <note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor: 5. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Eph. 2. 1, 5 Jude 12.</note> nature dead in Sin.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many ſorts of ſin are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 51. 4, 5. Tit: 1. 15, 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Original, &amp; Actual.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is Original Sin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="q" place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſal. 14. 1. Rom. 5. 10-19.</note> corruption of my Nature, accompanying the guilt of our firſt Parents tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>In what part is thy Nature corrupted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 14. 3. Titus 1. 15 1 Theſ. 5. 23</note> every part.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Doth it then reigne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, <note n="s" place="margin">Rom: 6. 12 &amp; 6. 14.</note> by Nature.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then thy life by Nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <note n="t" place="margin">Gen: 6. 5. Rom: 1. 29 Pſal: 40. 12.</note> multiplying of Actual ſin.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is actual Sin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="u" place="margin">Gen: 6. 12 Col: 3. 7.</note> corruption of my Life.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How many ſorts of actual ſin are there?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>w</hi> Mat: 15. 19 &amp; 5. 28, 32, 34 Pſal: 10. 4, 7</note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <label>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Three, namely evill</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>Thoughts.</item>
                        <item>Words.</item>
                        <item>Deeds.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How art thou miſerable in regard of pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In that I am <note n="x" place="margin">Rom: 1. 32. Rom: 3. 19 Rom: 6. 23. John 3 36.</note> worthy of Death</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat Death?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not only <note n="y" place="margin">Rom: 6. 23. &amp; 5. 12 &amp; 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. Mark 3. 22. Jude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> temporal, but eternal</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:191876:6"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is it enough to know this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No; <note n="a" place="margin">Rev: 3, 18 Acts 2. 37.</note> I muſt be humbled under it. 2 <hi>Chron. 36. 12. Dan.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How farr muſt thy humi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reach?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. To <note n="b" place="margin">Dan: 4. 27. Pſal. 51. 17.</note> break me off from my Sin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <note n="c" place="margin">Mat: 16: 24 Mat: 13. 46</note> drive me out of my ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To [<hi>d</hi>] make me ſee my need of a Saviour. <hi>Acts 9. 6. Mat:</hi> 9. 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>PART 2.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>HOw muſt thou come to be ſaved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Only <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 4. 12 Rom: 8. 2, 3.</note> by Jeſus Chriſt</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Who is Jeſus Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="f" place="margin">John 3. 16. 2 John 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> John 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. Mat: 1. 23. 1 Tim: 3. 16</note> Eternal Son of God who is both God &amp; man, in one Perſon</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why was Chriſt Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <note n="g" place="margin">Heb: 2. 9. Phil. 2. 8.</note> He might dy for me.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhy was Christ God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <note n="h" place="margin">Acts 20. 28 Heb: 9, 14.</note> by his Death, he might deliver me from death.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is He an alſufficient Saviour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes; <note n="i" place="margin">Mat: 9, 28. Heb: 7 21. Acts 3. 22, Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 5, 6 Pſal 2. 6. Ephe. 5. 23.</note> He is an Alſufficient Mediatour, Prophet, Preiſt, King and Head to his Church.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How hath he wrought for thee a perfect Salvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By his <note n="k" place="margin">Rom: 5. 19. Gal. 3. 13.</note> Obedience &amp; ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191876:6"/> he hath ſatisfied Divine Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 8. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: 3. 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26. Heb: 9. 12, 15</note> and purchaſed for us Reconciliation &amp; Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>Queſt <hi>How by his ſufferings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In <note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 3. 13 Rom: 5. 9. 2 Cor: 5. 21.</note> bearing the whole curſe due to me for my ſin.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How by his Obedience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <note n="m" place="margin">Heb: 10. 7. 8. 10. Rom: 4. 6. Mat: 5. 17. Eſay 9. 6.</note> doing the whole will of God for me.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is it enough to know this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, <note n="n" place="margin">John 5. 24. Acts 16. 31. John 10. 38. 2 Chron: 14. 11.</note> but I muſt believe in Chriſt alſo.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What meaneſt thou, when thou ſayeſt, I muſt believe in Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <note n="o" place="margin">John 6 35 John 3. 15. 2 Chron: 14. 11. &amp; 13. 18</note> I muſt Reſt upon him alone for life and ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Doth not faith admit of degrees?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, <note n="p" place="margin">Rom: 4. 19, 20. Mat. 14 31 15. 28. Luke 17. 2.</note> there is a weak, and a ſtrong ſaith. 2 <hi>Theſ 1. 3. Mat:</hi> 17. 20.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Can a weak Faith ſave?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes; <note n="q" place="margin">Zach: 7. 50 Eph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 4. 20. 15. 13. Col: 2, 2.</note> But a ſtrong faith brings aſſurance, and comfort with it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the fruits of ſaving Faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The two chief fruits are <note n="r" place="margin">Rom: 3. 1. Gal: 2. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Acts 15. 9. &amp; 26. 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>1. Iuſtification. 2. Sanctification</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it to be Juſtified?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="s" place="margin">Rom: 4. 5. 7</note> be pardoned our Sins;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191876:7"/> and accepted of God, as Righteous, in<note place="margin">2 Cor 5. 19, 20. Rom. 5. 18</note> his Chriſt unto Life.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it to be Sanctified?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="s" place="margin">Heb 9. 13. Heb: 1. 3. John 5. 21. 1 John 1. 9. Col: 3. 10, Rom: 6. 4.</note> be purged from our ſins and quickned by the Grace of Chriſt, unto Newnes of life.</p>
               <p>Queſt <hi>How is Faith wrought?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Outwardly <note n="t" place="margin">Rom: 10. 17 John 17. 20. Gal. 5. 22. 1 Cor: 12. 3.</note> by Gods Word: inwardly by his Spirit.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is Faith (&amp; Grace) ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and increaſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the right uſe of the <note n="u" place="margin">Acts 2. 42 Pſal: 119. 93. Luke 17. 5 Rom: 4. 11. 1 Cor: 11. 17 Mat 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19, 20</note> Word Prayer, Sacraments, and Fellowſhip.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How by the Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By <note n="w" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pet: 2. 1, 3 Gal: 3. 2. Rev: 1. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal: 1. 2 Mal: 3. 16.</note> the due hearing of the Word (preached) Reading, Meditation and Conference.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <note n="x" place="margin">1 Sam. 1. 15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: 25. 1 Ioh 16 23. 24 R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 26, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 1 Theſ: 5. 17, 18 1 John 5. 14</note> pouring out of the Soul before God, (or a lifting up of the Soul unto God) in the name of Chriſt, by the help of his Spirit, in way of Petition, or Thankſgiving.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not Confeſſion alſo a part of Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not our <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal: 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 65. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2 1 King. 8. 33. 35. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a 51 3 4. 5 &amp; <hi>ver 13 14.</hi>
                  </note> Confeſſions only but our Vows alſo, are to be made to God in Prayer, and either of them are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191876:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> meerly adjoyned to Petition, or Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.<note place="margin">Pſal: 116. 2, 11, 14</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Rule of direction have wee for Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſame which Chriſt <note n="z" place="margin">Mat: 6. 9 Luke 11. 12.</note> taught us, ſaying, Our Father which art in Heaven &amp;c:</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is a Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A viſible <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 2. 36, 37 Rom: 4. 11 Gen: 17. 11. 1 Cor: 10 2. 4. Mat: 26 26, 28</note> Sign and Seal of the Covenant, or promiſe of Grace.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is this Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Covenant <note n="b" place="margin">Gen: 17 1, 7 &amp; 9. Exo. 6, 7 Hoſea 2. 13 Heb: 8. 10 Mat: 26. 28 &amp; 28. 19, 20 Col: 3, 9</note> which God hath ſtricken with his faithfull people and their ſeed; that they be his People and He their God.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How comes this Covenant to be made good to us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Only by Chriſt, <note n="c" place="margin">Heb: 7. 22 &amp; 9. 15 1 Tim: 2. 5 2 Cor: 1. 20.</note> who is the Mediatour therof.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many Sacraments are there appointed us, whereby Chriſt and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits are ſignified &amp; ſealed to us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two only now under the Goſpel, namely <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 2. 41, 42. Mat: 28. 19. 1 Cor: 11. 23. 1 Cor: 12. 13</note> Baptiſm, and the Supper of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why do we Baptiſe Infants, ſeing the Sacraments do ſerve to confirme and encreaſe Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:191876:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 2. 39. 2 Cor: 7. 14.</note> the Children of Confederate Believers are under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Grace, and within the Covenant</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why do we admit only grown perſons to the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it ſignifies our <note n="f" place="margin">John 6. 55 1 Cor: 11. 28 29, 31.</note> growth in Chriſt, and it is required in the Receiver, that there be an ability of diſcerning and judging how it is with himſelf that way.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is that fellowſhip you spake of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <note n="g" place="margin">Acts 2. 42 47. 1 Cor: 10 16, 17. 1 John 1. 3, 7 1 Cor: 12. 13 27. Phil. 1. 5.</note> holy Communion, which the Members of true viſible Churches, are by the <hi>Bond of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> to exerciſe joyntly with God in Chriſt, and mutually one with another, according to the Rule of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is that Bond of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant you named?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <note n="h" place="margin">Mat: 16. 16, 17. 2 Cor: 9 13. Heb: 10. 22. 25. Heb: 3. 1, 6. &amp; 4. 14, 16. 2 Cor: 8. 5 Pſal 133. 1. Neh: 10. 28 Hoſea 2 23 Eph. 4. 16.</note> holy profeſſion which they make, (according to the tenour of this Covenant) of their giving up themſelves and their ſeed to the Lord firſt, and then to his People; to be his, and theirs in him for the promoting of his Honour &amp; worſhip, &amp; their mutual edification</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:191876:8"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin lyeth the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion they be joyntly to exerciſe towards God in Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <note n="i" place="margin">Heb: 10. 22 25. Pſal. 73. 28 &amp; 27. 4 Pſa: 84. 2 &amp; c: John 1. 12 Col: 2. 19</note> drawing neer unto, and enjoying of him through Faith, in his own wayes &amp; Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin lyeth the Communion they profeſs to exerciſe mutually among themſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In their <note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor: 12. 7 &amp; 22. 1 Pet: 4. 10 Rom: 1. 11. 12, 13. Coloſ. 2. 19</note> mutual participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the benefit of the gifts and graces of each other.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Theſe being the outward meanes of our ſpiritual growth, Tell me now what is required to the due uſe of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor: 3. 18 1 Cor: 12. 3 Rom: 8. 26 Mat: 18. 20 &amp; 28. 20.</note> preſence and help of Gods Spirit.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may we know when our faith is true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1 If it be <note n="m" place="margin">Rom: 1. 16 17.</note> wrought &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed (as hath been been ſhewed) namely, in Gods wayes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be in a heart truely humbled.<note place="margin">1 Pet: 5. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If it be grounded upon a word<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 19 &amp; 42 Mat: 11. 28, 29</note> of promiſe, and the free Grace of God in Chriſt teſtified therin.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If it be accompanied with an<note place="margin">Acts 15. 9 2 Cor: 5. 17 Eph. 4. 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24</note> univerſal change.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:191876:9"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How may we know, when we do grow in faith &amp; grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If there be a <note n="n" place="margin">1 Pet: 2. 2. Luke 17. 5. Phil: 3. 13. Rev: 21. 6</note> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vely deſire and endeavour after growth</p>
               <p n="2">2. If there be a <note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor: 6. 17 2 Pet: 1. 4 1 John 5. 18.</note> carefull ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from what hindereth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If there be the <note n="p" place="margin">Eſay 4. 4.</note> ſpirit of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of burning.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If there be a <note n="q" place="margin">Phil: 2. 21 Mat: 6. 33</note> ſeeking mainly of the things of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If there be a <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor: 11. 17 Phil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. 13 Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 92. 13</note> ſpiritual ſtriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to do every duty better: and to gain by every Ordinance more.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If there be an <note n="s" place="margin">Phil. 1. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11 Col<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 10 1 Theſ. 4. 1.</note> increaſing and abounding more and more in all holy fruitfullneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>PART 3.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHerein lyeth the Duty, and thankfullneſs required?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tit: 2. 11, 12 Luk. 1. 74, 75 1 Pet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 1, 2</note> leading a new &amp; holy Life.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who leads this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He who <note n="u" place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12 1 Theſ. 4. 7 Phil: 2. 15 Acts 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 16 Rom: 6. 13</note> ſtrives unfainedly and conſtantly, by the grace of Chriſt, to live, not only in no known S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, but alſo in the neglect of no known Duty.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Root of a godly L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> True <note n="w" place="margin">1 Tim: 1. 5 Acts 15: 9 Heb: 11: 6 Gal: 2: 20</note> Faith which worketh by Love.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:191876:9"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Rule of a Godly life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="x" place="margin">2 Tim: 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2 Pet: 1. 19 Ephe: 2. 20 Jam. 2. 8, 12</note> Word of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Old &amp; New Teſtament, Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marily compriſed in the Moral Law, or the Ten Commandements.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of a Godly life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1 The avoyding of all <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal: 34. 12, 14 Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y 1. 16. 17 Eph: 4. 22, 24</note> evill forbidden. 2 The doing of every duty Commanded.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What if through infirmitie, there be a ſtepping aſide from the holy Rule in either of theſe particulars?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are to be carefull <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke 13. 3 Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: 32 tot: Pſal: 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. tot: Rev: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5 &amp; 16 Luke 17. 3</note> out of hand, to recouer our ſelves by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <note n="a" place="margin">Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 26. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20 &amp; Act. 14 15 Jer: 31. 18, 19 2 Cor: 7. 10, 11</note> turning of the whole man from Sin, unto God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the Ends of a Godly life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <note n="b" place="margin">2 Pet: 1. 5, 10 Mat: 5. 16 Gal: 1. 13. 24 1 Pet: 3. 1 2 Theſ: 1. 11 12 1 Cor: 10 31<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> making ſure our own Calling and Election: with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual good of others, and cheifly Gods Glory.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To what end doth the Lord lay afflictions upon the godly in this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. For their <note n="c" place="margin">Heb: 12. 10 Eſay 27. 9</note> Profit, that they might be partakers of his Holines.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:191876:10"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Are not the Saints then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. There <note n="d" place="margin">Luke 17. 10 Phil: 3 12, 13 14 1 Pet: 5. 10</note> are none ſo perfect but they ought to endeavour dayly after more &amp; more Settlement So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity, Stability, and perfection in all Grace and Godlines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="appendix">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN APPENDIX</hi> Firſt TOUCHING PRAYER</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">U</seg>Pon what grounds call you the Lords Prayer, a Pattern Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. Becauſe <note n="a" place="margin">Mat: 6. 9 Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. 1, 2</note> it was given to that end.</p>
               <p>2. Becauſe it yields Direction touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both the Matter, and the Manner, or Method of Prayer.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat things are obſervable in this Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. The Prayer it ſelf.</p>
               <p>2. The Illuſtration of it.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:191876:10"/>
               <p>By 1. A Preface before it, in the words, (Our Father which art in heaven</p>
               <p>2. A concluſion afer it, in the word (Amen.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What doth this Order and Method uſed by our Saviour in this Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er teach us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Somthing required of us,<note place="margin">The Preface</note>
               </p>
               <p>Both, in the time of Prayer;</p>
               <p>And alſo, before, and after Prayer.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What doth the Preface teach us to attend before Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The qualification of the perſon, A child by Adoption, as who hath <note n="b" place="margin">Rom: 8. 15. Zach: 12. 10</note> God his Father.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal: 10. 17. 2 Chron: 12. 14.</note> preparation of the heart unto the Duty.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is the heart duely prepared for Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When it comes unto it, with <note n="d" place="margin">Gen: 18. 27 Pſal: 2. 11. Eccl: 5. 1. James 1. 6 1 Tim: 2. 8 Mat: 5. 24 John 4. 23.</note> due Reverence, Humility, Faith, Love and Charity: and with heavenlynes or Spiritualnes of mind.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What help is here afforded herunto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are here taught to look at God in prayer, as 1. A Father, in reſpect of his <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay 63. 16. Pſal: 103. 13</note> tender Mercy and affection.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:191876:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. A heavenly-Father, as who is an <note n="f" place="margin">Mat: 6. 32. 1 King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. 27. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v: 1. 8. Gen: 17. 1 Heb: 4. 13. 1 Tim: 1. 17.</note> Infinite, Incomprehenſible and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Being, the Omnipotent, Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and onely wiſe God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our Father, <note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor: 6 16 18.</note> as who is, what He thus is for us.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>As touching the time of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what doth the Brevity, &amp; yet pithines of the Prayer it ſelf teach?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That our prayers be <note n="h" place="margin">James 5. 16 Mat: 6. 7, 8 Eccl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 1.</note> Fervent and Sincere.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How many parts are there of (this) Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, 1 Requeſt (to-deliver us<note place="margin">Phil: 4. 6.</note> from evill. 2 Thankſgiving, (at-for thine is the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Order &amp; Method of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Order of the Pet:</note> 
                  <hi>the matter preſented in this prayer teach?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That we are as well <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal: 50. 15 Luke 17. 13, 18.</note> to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for, as we are to beg good things.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That both in our Requeſts and Thankſgivings, we are to preferr,</p>
               <p>1 The things of <note n="k" place="margin">John 7. 18.</note> God before our own. 2 Thoſe of <note n="l" place="margin">Phil: 2. 20,</note> publick before thoſe of private concernment.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Spiritual <note n="m" place="margin">Mat: 6. 33.</note> bleſſings before temporal.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:191876:11"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How many heads of Petition or Requeſt are there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Six.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How may this Petitionary part be Sub-divided?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Into two parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Apprecatory: in the 4 firſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Deprecatory: in the 2 laſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may this teach us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That the <note n="n" place="margin">Phil 4. 6.</note> Deprecation of evill is as warrantable, and needfull in<note place="margin">p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 7 8. 13 &amp; of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lms.</note> its place, as is the Apprecation of good.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What diviſion would you make of the Apprecatory part?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It doth contain Petitions for good things, as they concern, Firſtly God. Secondly Man. And theſe in the firſt place reſpecting his ſpiritual life Secondly his temporal life. The things which belong unto his ſpiritual condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are conſidered as reſpecting,</p>
               <p>Firſt the Grace of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Secondly the Obedience required of man to the Lawes of the Kingdom, or Will of our King himſelf.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What learn we hence in particular concerning the manner of Requeſting good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:191876:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That the matter of theſe four ſeveral heads of petition have ſuch a dependance each upon other, as the ſecond is ſubordinate to the firſt; the third to the ſecond, and firſt; and the fourth to the three foregoing petitions orderly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the former afford matter of argument to enforce the following.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That temporal good things are<note place="margin">Mat: 26. 39, 42.</note> not to be begged, but conditionally.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat doth that Petition (Hallowed be thy Name) concern?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">PET: 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Glory of Gods great Name.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are we taught to beg in this petition in general?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 48. 10. &amp; 115. 1. Ezek 36. 20, 23. Exod: 9. 10. Neh 9. 10 Pſal: 29. 2. Eſay 29 23. Ezek: 20. 9, 14. 22, 44</note> God would ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule all things in the world as the Glory of his Name may be provided for.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What in particular?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The <note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet: 3, 15 Pſal: 50 23. 2 Theſ. 1. 10 12. 1 Pet: 2. 9, 12. &amp; 4. 10 11, 14, 16.</note> enabling of us by his Grace, to become every way in our Times, inſtrumental of his Glory.</p>
               <p>2. The <note n="q" place="margin">Rom: 15. 8, 9. 2 Sam: 7. 25, 26 Pſal. 79. 9. Rom: 11. 33, 36. 2 The. 1. 9</note> fullfilling of the word of his promiſe to his Church &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ones: and of his threatnings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemies of his Name.</p>
               <p>Pſal. 75. 1. Eſa. 63. 12, 14. with 64. 12.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:191876:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What graces are here to bee ſought by prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Principally the <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 9. 10, 11. Pſal. 86. 11, 12. Pſal. 69. 9. &amp; 36.</note> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, fear, and love of Gods Name.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Confeſſion being an adjunct of prayer, what evills do we learn here to be confeſsed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All our <note n="s" place="margin">Jer: 48. 17. Pſal: 44. 20. Mal. 3. 14. Pſal: 40. 10. Jer: 10. 25 Exod: 20. 7 1 Tim: 6. 1 2 Sam: 12. 14. Rom: 2. 24 Rev: 2, 13.</note> Ignorance of Gods Name, forgetfulneſs of it, concealing of it, with the neglect of calling upon that his Name: and in a word all manner of our taking his name in vain.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="t" place="margin">2 King. 19. 1, 4. Pſal: 119 136, &amp; 158. PET: 2.</note> prophaning, abuſing, or blaſpheming of his Name by others</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What doth the ſecond head of Petitions teach us to aſk of God in prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> The communication of <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal: 63. 1, 2, 3. Rom 14 17. 1 Cor: 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4, 9. Luke 17 20, 21. 1 Pet: 1. 8. Pſal: 4. 6. Exod: 33. 15. Pſal: 106. 4, 5</note> Himſelf, Spirit &amp; Grace, in the inward efficacy, and outward ſignal Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his ſpecial Preſence &amp; favour</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What more particularly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1 The <note n="w" place="margin">Pſal: 69<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24 35. Rev: 11. 17, 18. Pſal. 68. 1, 2. Rom: 6. 6. 1 John 3. 8. Rom: 16. 20 2 Tim: 2. 26.</note> caſting down of Satans kingdom, with all its props, be they perſons or things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal 51. 18. Mat: 6. 33. Eſay 62. 7. 2 Theſ: 3. 1.</note> Erecting of his own Kingdom in the world, where it is not, and the maintaining &amp; increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191876:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> of it where it is: as concerns both<note place="margin">Pſal. 122. 6. Eph. 6. 18, 19 Pſal 51. 12 Eſay 9. 7 Col: 2. 19. 1 Theſ 3. 12.</note> the inward grace, and outward admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations therof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <note n="y" place="margin">Ruth 4. 11 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ephe 6. 4. Gen: 18: 19 1 Tim: 2. 2 Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 49 22, 23 2 Kin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 1, 2 Pſal. 80. 17. Eſa. 19. 19, 20 Dan: 12. 1.</note> graunting and bleſſing ſuch means as may advantage hereunto: Such as godly family nurture, civil Government, Schools of learning &amp;c:</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <note n="z" place="margin">Rev: 22. 20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tim: 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8</note> haſtning the Kingdom of Glory.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the ſpecial Graces as concerns the Kingdom of God, that we are here to pray for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The <note n="a" place="margin">Mat: 13. 11. Mat: 11. 23. Ephe: 1. 17, 18, 19.</note> enlightning our underſtandings to diſcern the miſteries of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 36. 26. Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: 2. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>: 5. 3.</note> Teachable ſelf-denying frame of heart to ſubject to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment therof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The uſe of <note n="c" place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8: 23, 24. Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 2 John 4. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor: 3. 18.</note> Faith, Hope, and Love, with ſincerity, as neceſſary to the enjoying of ſpiritual Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with God, in the wayes and adminiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations therof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Patience under the croſs, which they<note place="margin">
                     <hi>d</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t: 5. 10 Mat: 16. 24,</note> that receive this Kingdom muſt expect</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What matter of confeſſion is here preſented unto us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 7. 24. &amp; 10. 3. Luke 19. 42.</note> Corruption of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191876:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> and its fruits in the blindneſs<note place="margin">Mat: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 58 Luke 16 14. 16. &amp; 12. 32 J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes 4. 6. John 3. 1, 2</note> of the mind, in infidelity, pride, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-mindednes, ſlaviſh fear &amp;c:</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What elſe may we here lament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal: 79. 8. &amp; 80. 12, 13. &amp; 79. 1. 2 Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1, 2, 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am: 5. 8. 18. Pſal: 14. 1, 2 Mat: 23, 13. &amp; 15. 6, 13. Col: 2. 20, 23 2 Theſ. 2. 4, 7 Eſay 63. 5. Mat: 9. 36, 38<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> low eſtate of the Church, the inſolency and prevalency of the common enemy, the atheiſm, impiety, and groſs idolatry of the world with all the ſuperſtition, and humane inventions &amp; corruptions crept into the Church: &amp; any defect of preſent means of redreſs. 1 <hi>Tim. 6. 3, 4, 5. Jude</hi> 13, 18, 19</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What doth the third head of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">PET: 3.</note> 
                  <hi>petitions, in thoſe words (Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven) teach us to ſue for in prayer?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Chron: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 30. Num: 28. 4. Jo. 15. 4, 5. Heb: 12. 28 Phil. 2. 12, 13 Gal: 2. 20 Col: 1. 9, 11 1 Cor: 15. 58 1 Pet 5. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The [<hi>g</hi>] dayly freſh-ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of all needfull grace, as to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling of us to both the doing and enduring Gods will, and the perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therin, unto all well-pleaſing to him</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What more particularly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal: 143. 8. 10. Pſal. 119. 125 &amp; 18. &amp; 18. &amp; 27. Pſal: 86. 11.</note> making known his will unto us, both what he would have us to do, and how to do it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal: 119. 10 11, 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 63 &amp; 67. Hoſea 6. 3. John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 30. John 7. 17.</note> enclining of our hearts to attend diligently all due means, for the finding out what his will is with us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:191876:14"/> and for the forming of them into the<note place="margin">Pſal: 119. 36. 100, &amp; 106. Gal: 4. 19. 1 Cor: 9. 27.</note> obedience therof.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The <note n="k" place="margin">1 King. 13. 19. 20, 21. Acts 21, 14.</note> ſubjecting our wills to his will, now once manifeſted. <hi>Pſ. 40. 8 Mat. 7. 21. Joh.</hi> 5. 30. &amp; 6. 38. <hi>Ro.</hi> 12. 1</p>
               <p n="4">4 The <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal: 119. 35 &amp; 27. 11. &amp; 5. 8. &amp; 51. 11 12: Phil. 1. 19 Mat: 28 20</note> aſſiſtance of his Spirit, to carry us an end our endeavours in that reſpect.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The <note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor 19. 5 Pſal: 119. 39. &amp; 134. Zech: 9. 8.</note> taking the letts out of the way, whither ſuch as are within, or ſuch as are without us.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal: 148. 8. Zech: 3. 2 Job 5. 12.</note> diſapointing their wills which are oppoſite to Gods will.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>In what manner is Gods will to be done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In every part of it, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duties of either general or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar calling, doing or ſuffering what we are called to, according to the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pattern before us.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But the holy Angels &amp; ſpirits of the just ones in heaven, not being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſufferings, Wherin ſhould we imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet: 2. 20. Deut: 5. 33 Ephe: 6. 6 Acts 2. 46 2 Cor: 9. 7 Pſal: 119. 32. &amp; 60. Phil: 2, 14 Pſal: 119<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6 1 Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: 28. 7 Gal: 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In doing or attending Gods will Sincerely, ſpeedily, cheerfully, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, conſtantly and unweariably.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Graces are we taught here
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:191876:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> eſpecially to ſeek?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A right <note n="o" place="margin">Pſa. 119. 128 &amp; 97 Pſa<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18 21, 23. Pſal: 119. 32. Pſal: 51. 12 2 Kin: 22. 19</note> eſteem of Gods word &amp; wayes: Love and delight in the ſame, an upright and enlarged heart or free ſpirit, with the hatred of every evill way, and tenderneſs of conſcience.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What matter of confeſſion, or lamentation is preſented under this third head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor: 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pro: 2. 14, 15 Pſal: 18 26 Jer: 4. 22 James 3. 15 2 Cor: 1. 12 2 Cor: 10. 5, 6 2 Chron: 36<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16.</note> natural impotency, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes, and deadnes to that is good, the wiſdom of the freſh, and carnall reaſonings oppoſing, and the ſlight ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Gods word, miniſters, and wayes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other matter of this ſort?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal: 32. 23 Jer: 17. 9 Pro: 26. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. Jer: 9. 10 Pſal: 78 57 Mal: 1. 13 Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17. 10 1 John 3, 4.</note> guile, ſloth, unchear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes, unfaithfullnes, and weariſomnes attending us, when we are about any good, with all the imperfection of our obedience, and all ſuch our thoughts, ſpeeches &amp; actions, as ſuite not to the will of God.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What further matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint this way?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="r" place="margin">2 Tim: 3. 8. Rom: 10. 21 Titus 1. 16 2 Pet: 2. 2 Acts 19. 9.</note> great hatred and oppoſition in the world, againſt the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:191876:15"/> Truth, Will, and wayes of God.<note place="margin">Acts 28. 22</note>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we taught under that Fourth head of Petitions, (Give us</hi>
                  <note place="margin">PET: 3.</note> 
                  <hi>this day, our dayly bread?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gods <note n="s" place="margin">Mat: 7. 11. Mat: 6. 32 Pro: 30. 8.</note> Fatherly care &amp; compaſſion, to the dayly ſupplying of us, with the outward neceſſaries and comforts of this life.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat be they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as; <note n="t" place="margin">Gen: 28. 20 21 Col: 4. 14 Pſal: 104. 14, 15, 16. Deut: 26. 2 3 John 2. Pſal: 39. 13 Pſal: 4. 8. &amp; 147. 14 Acts 12. 5 Heb: 13. 23 Acts 16. 25</note> Food, Rayment, and Phiſick: health &amp; ſtrength of body in the right uſe of them. Outward peace, ſafety &amp; liberty, with the means therof: and the removal or preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what tends to the prejudice of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat more particularly are we taught here to pray for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Such creature <note n="u" place="margin">Deut. 28. 11 Pſal: 37. 17 &amp; 24, 25 Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 34. 9, 10, 19 &amp; 36. 6</note> comforts as are needfull for the ſupportation, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation or reſtauration of our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such ſuitable <note n="w" place="margin">Ruth 4. 15 Gen 24. 63 Pro: 19. 14. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1 10 Pſal: 28. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Deut: 28, 3.</note> relations, or ſuch ſuitablenes in relations, with ſuch abilities, ſkill, faithfulnes on their parts, as may conduce to our outward comfort.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such wholeſom <note n="x" place="margin">1 Kings 10 8, 9.</note> Laws,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:191876:15"/> Government, and order in Civil ſociety<note place="margin">Rom: 13. 4. 1 Tim: 2. 2</note> as conduce to a quiet &amp; peacable life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The enjoying a <note n="y" place="margin">Exo: 20. 15 1 Cor: 3. 22, 23. Rom. 8. 17</note> Civil, and religious right to our enjoyments.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The bleſſing of our honeſt labours<note place="margin">Pſal: 127. 1. Pro: 10. 22 Deut: 28. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> travells &amp; endeavours, for the procur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any of them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Are there not more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of this nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, as 1. The <note n="z" place="margin">2 King. 2. 19. &amp; 6. 1, 2 Pſal: 16. 5, 6 Acts 17. 26. 1 Cor: 7. 20 Pſal: 54. 4 1 Chron: 27. 33.</note> ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us with meet means, &amp; advantages, in this reſpect, as a meet place of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, meet imployments, meet aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance &amp;c:</p>
               <p>2. The <note n="a" place="margin">Deut: 28. 4. Hag: 2. 6 2 Tim: 4. 4</note> bleſſing of all ſuch our enjoyments, to our uſe.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What things are they, which do prejudice our outward life, and the comfort of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sickneſſes, <note n="b" place="margin">Deu: 28. 20 to 44. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal: 91. 10 Hag: 2. 17 2 Tim: 3, 1, 3 Amos 4. 6, 10 2. Chron: 15. 5, 6 Mat: 24. 7 Ezek: 5. 17</note> and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of the body, outward caſualtyes, and loſſes of the creature, unſeaſonable weather, ſtrife and diviſion amongſt neighbours, the oppreſſion, &amp; unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of ſuch as we live with, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick diſturbances in the Common-weal, or any of thoſe judgments of the ſword peſtelence &amp; famine.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:191876:16"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſpecial graces are wee here taught to ſue for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Confidence <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal: 37. 5, 7 &amp; ver: 34 Gen: 32. 10</note> in God, as relying upon his Fatherly Providence, a hopeful wayting Gods time and ſeaſon, and humility, as willing to be beholding to him, for the leaſt of his mercyes.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sobriety, and <note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet: 5. 8 Phil: 4. 5, 11 Rom: 12. 15 &amp; 15. 3.</note> moderation in the purſuit &amp; uſe of theſe things; contentation with our preſent portion and a Sympathy with the Saints, in their outward condition.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What portion of theſe outward things are we to eſteem the fitteſt for u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. That which the wiſdom of our <note n="e" place="margin">Mat: 7. 11</note> heavenly-Father carves out unto us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which <note n="f" place="margin">Pro: 30. 8. 9</note> expoſeth us leaſt to tempation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That which is <note n="g" place="margin">Deu: 28. 47 Mat: 6. 33<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1 Pet: 4. 10, 12.</note> neereſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the meaſure of grace communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and is moſt advantagious to our communion with God; and to our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual growth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What evills are we taught here to confeſs?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:191876:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Carnal <note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor: 1. 9 Pſal: 146. 3 &amp; 20. 7 Mark 10. 24</note> confidence, whether in our ſelves, or in any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Carking <note n="i" place="margin">Heb: 13. 5 Mat: 6. 25, 26 1 Tim: 6. 9 1 Theſ: 4. 6</note> care, and diſtruſt of Gods Providence, with the ſinfull fruits thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Diſcontent, and <note n="k" place="margin">Exo: 16. 2, 3 Num: 11. 4, 5 Pſa: 78. 28, 29</note> murmuring at our preſent condition.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Envying <note n="l" place="margin">Pro: 3. 31 Pſal: 37. 1, 7</note> at the proſperity of others.</p>
               <p n="5">5. All <note n="m" place="margin">Pro: 18. 9 &amp; 19. 15 2 Theſ: 3. 10 John 6. 12 Mat: 24. 38 Pro: 21. 17 &amp; 23. 30 Amos 6. 6</note> idlenes, improvidence intemperancy, and luxury, ſinfull am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and ſelviſhnes, and incompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionatnes. <hi>Rom: 13. 13. Jer: 45. 5. Phil. 2. 21. 2 Tim: 3. 2. Mat:</hi> 25. 42, 45.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we to deprecate, or</hi>
                  <note place="margin">PET: 5.</note> 
                  <hi>to pray againſt under the two following heads of petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the <note n="n" place="margin">Hoſea 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> evill of ſin: Both the guilt &amp; puniſhment of ſin; as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the time paſt, (under the 5.<hi rend="sup">t</hi> head) and the prevailing of remaining corruption, together with the cauſes, or means conducing to the committing of ſin: reſpecting time to come, (under the ſixt &amp; laſt head of petitions.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What may we conceive, we are taught hence?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:191876:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. That <note n="o" place="margin">Rom: 2. 23 Eſay 59. 2 Jer: 5. 25</note> the due care of Gods glory, of our communion w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th God, &amp; even of enjoying the comfort of our dayly bread; doeth enflame in a child of God, a ſincere deſire of the taking away of ſin, as the great lett therof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal: 51. 9. 10 &amp; 79. 8, 9</note> we as well do ſeek of God, to be kept from ſin for the time to come, as to be pardoned our ſin paſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal: 32. 3, 4, 5 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 2 Sam: 11, &amp; 12 Pſal: 39. 8 &amp; 41. 4 1 John 1. 9 Pſal: 85 2, 8</note> the neglect of ſueing out a pardon, for ſin already commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; makes way for us, to be delivered up of God, to the committing of yet more ſin.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What then more particularly are we taught to pray under the fift head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal: 130. 3, 4 &amp; 32. 1, 2 Rom: 4. 6 Pſal: 51. 1, 2 Pſal: 25. 7</note> not-imputing to us, our ſins: but contrariwiſe the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting &amp; applying the Righteouſnes of Chriſt to us to our juſtification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <note n="s" place="margin">Pſal: 51. 7, 12 &amp; 14 Pſal: 25. 7 Joel 2. 14 Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: 8, 15 Col: 2 2 Ephe: 1. 7</note> not leaving us under darknes, &amp; doubt in this reſpect; but the clearing up unto our ſoules, his acceptance of us in his Chriſt through the freenes, &amp; riches of his grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal: 103. 8, 12. &amp; 69. 16, 17 &amp; 38. 1 Heb: 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6</note> not deſerting of us in time of affliction, or of his frowning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:191876:17"/> diſpenſations: but the ſo appearing<note place="margin">Pſal: 13. 1 Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y 63. 9 Cant: 3. 10 E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay 38. 17 Hoſ. 14. 4, 7</note> unto us in the ſame, (as in all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of his Grace:) as we may perceive his Fatherly-love to us therin</p>
               <p n="4">4. The not <note n="u" place="margin">Dan: 9. 19 1 Kings 8. 49 50 1 Joh: 2. 1 Pſal: 40. 11, 12 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 16, 17 Ephe: 1: 7, 14 with 4: 30</note> deferring, but haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the full execution of that gracious ſentence of abſolution pronounced in our juſtification.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why is this added (as we forgive them that trespaſs against us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To ſhew that <note n="w" place="margin">Mat: 5: 7 Mat: 6: 14 Mat: 5: 44, 45 Mat: 18: 21 to 35 Ephe: 4: 31</note> ſuch (as in whom this holy diſpoſition is found) may with the more confidence urge, &amp; expect, the obtaining forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes at Gods hands.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How farr forth ſhould wee forgive others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. So farr forth as <note n="x" place="margin">Mat: 18. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 22 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mark 2. 7</note> the offence is an injury to us.</p>
               <p>2. So far forth as <note n="y" place="margin">Mat: 18: 15, 21 Luke 17: 3, 4 1 Cor: 10: 31 1 Cor: 8: 9, 13 1 Cor: 6: 1, 4 1 Tim. 2: 2</note> the glory of Gods Name, their own ſpiritual good, and the due preſervation of our own right, in a way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; charity, may be regularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What graces are we taught then to beg for, under this head of petition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Repentance <note n="z" place="margin">1 Kings 8 46: 48</note> and humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:191876:18"/> for ſin, ſpringing from the true<note place="margin">Rom:: 5: 1:</note> knowledge of our ſelves, &amp; ſin; &amp; of Chriſt, and him crucifyed: and peace, flowing from the application of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="a" place="margin">Rom: 8: 15 Zech: 12: 12 Rom: 14: 17 Pſal: 18. 25</note> ſpirit of Adoption, joy in the Holy ghoſt, with mercifulnes and readines to forgive others.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the ſpeciall ſins to be lamented?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Impenitency <note n="b" place="margin">Rom: 2: 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>e: 4: 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>: 32: 2</note> hardnes of heart, benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mednes of conſcience, with Guile in the matter of confeſſion and Repentance.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What evils elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Carnal <note place="margin">Job 12: 6 Deut: 29. 19 Lam: 3: 18 1 Tim: 2. 8 Rom: 12. 17, 19.</note> ſecurity, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods mercy, implacablenes, or backwardnes to forgive, &amp; forget injuries: Hatred &amp; deſire of Revenge.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we taught particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to deprecate vnder the ſixt head, in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">PET: 6.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe words (lead vs not into temptation, but deliver us from evill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> 1. Gods <note n="d" place="margin">Rom: 1: 24 2 Sam: 24: 1 2 Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: 15: 2 Pſal: 27: 9 Hoſea 5: 6</note> anger, in the ſad effects thereof, in his leaving or forſaking of us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <note n="e" place="margin">Mich: 7: 18 19</note> power or ſtrength of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:191876:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> our own corruptions, and what ever<note place="margin">Rom: 13. 14 Pſal: 19. 13. Pſal: 63. 1 Eſay 6. 5 Pſal: 120. 5. Mat: 26. 41</note> tends to the feeding, or exciting of the ſame. <hi>Pſal. 39. 1, 2. Jam:</hi> 1. 14, 15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <note n="f" place="margin">2 Pet: 2. 9, 10. 1 Tim: 6. 9</note> prevailing provocations and flateries (or threats) of the world.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 16. 20 Ephe: 6. 11, 12, 18.</note> ſuggeſtions &amp; tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Devil, and the prevayling of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Unſanctified <note n="h" place="margin">Pro: 13 9. 1 Cor: 10. 13 Dan: 8. 10. 18 Pſal: 69. 22</note> afflictions, of what kind ſo ever, yea &amp; unſanctified proſperity too.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Spiritual <note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor: 2. 8, 11. Jude 24. Luke 8. 13</note> defection, or apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acy from the truth of God in our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or from the way of God in our practiſe, as the effect of any of theſe.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What Graces are we taught particularly to beg?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal: 80. 18 Pſal: 119. 36 37, 88. Pſal: 68. 28 2 Tim: 4. 18. 1 Pet: 5. 10 Eph. 6. 11, 18</note> quickning Grace of Gods Spirit, all ſtrengthning and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting grace: with all the ſeverall peices of the ſpiritual Armour.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> His bleſſing <note n="l" place="margin">Eſa 27. 9 Pſal: 133. 3 Gal: 6. 1. 1 Cor: 5. 5 Col: 4, 12.</note> of all good means for the mortifying of corruption repreſſing of temptation, ſtrengthning of Faith, and the helping forward our recovery, when fallen: and our ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and perſeverance, when recovered.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:191876:19"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What elſe is here ſough?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The <note n="m" place="margin">1 Joh: 5. 4. 1 Cor: 15. 57 Rev: 2. 7, 17, 26. Rev: 3. 5, 12, 21. Rom: 8. 37.</note> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nal conqueſt and victory, over all our ſpirituall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies through the grace of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>lis are we taught here to lament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w.</hi> 1. What ever ſin may provoke God, to give us over to be tempted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What ever miſcariages may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Adverſary, and ſo lay us open to his Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons</p>
               <p n="3">3 Such evill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as may occaſion the Lord to withdraw himſelf, in time of temptation.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may be ſome of the ſpecials that may provoke the Lord, to ſuffer us to be tempted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Carnal <note n="n" place="margin">Luke 21. 34 36. Mat: 26. 33. 35 2 Theſ. 2. 11, 12. Gal. 5. 13. 2 Tim: 3. 2. &amp; 5. Luk. 22 55, 56 2 Tim: 4. 10. with Mat: 13 20, 21</note> ſecurity, Self confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, unprofitableneſs under Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the abuſe of our chriſtian liberty, ſinfull ſelf love, Formality in Gods Worſhip, and a careleſs ruſhing upon a temptation, with the favouring any one ſin in our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are they by which the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary is encouraged?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As the <note n="o" place="margin">2 Pet: 2. 13 with 19.</note> dallying with any ſin
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:191876:19"/> gives him boldneſs; or the ſuffering of<note place="margin">James 1. 14 with Gal. 3. 24. James 4. 7, 8. 2 Sam 11. 1, 2 1 Tim: 5. 12. 13. Eccl. 2. 1. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 King: 11. 1 4. Pſal. 39. 1 2.</note> any unmortified luſt: So in ſpecial, the neglect of Gods Ordinances, idlenes &amp; ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligence in our callings, the delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in carnal mirth, and pleaſures, vain company, needleſs ſolitarynes, and ſlaviſh fear &amp; cowardice; with many ſuch like. <hi>Eccl 4. 12. 1 Pet:</hi> 5. 8, 9.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat ſpecialls are there, cauſing Gods withdrawment of his Grace in time of Temptation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="p" place="margin">James 1. 6. 7. Job 22. 21 Pro: 13. 4, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 Sam: 13. 8, 9 Pro: 3. 11 Ephe: 4. 27 Eſay 30. 1, 2.</note> wavering of our Faith, ſtrangenes towards God, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſloth &amp; careleſneſs, impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of ſpirit, a growing ſoon weary of affliction, a giving way unto the Temptation, the uſe of indirect means in any caſe, and the like.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat reaſons have you why</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Doxolo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie.</note> 
                  <hi>you do take theſe words, [For thine is the Kingdom, the Power and the Glory, for ever,] to point out the thanksgiving and ſo a direction for the special matter and manner of that part of prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Becauſe, Thanks-giving being a part of prayer, muſt have ſome place, in this ſo perfect a Pattern.</p>
               <p>2. Becauſe, in other platforms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:191876:20"/> by the Spirit of God, we find <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal: 54 56 57 59 &amp; 61</note> thankſ-giving (ſometimes) to cloſe the ſame. 3. Becauſe, the [<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>]<note place="margin">
                     <hi>r</hi> Phil: 4. 6 Col: 4 2</note> expreſs Rule requires the joyning thanksgiving with petition.</p>
               <p>4. Becauſe, this very form of words<note place="margin">
                     <hi>s</hi> Rev<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 17 Rev: 12. 10 &amp; 19. 1 Jude 24, 25 &amp; in ſpecial 1 Chron: 29. 12, 13</note> is mentioned in other Scriptures, by way of Thankſgiving.</p>
               <p>Queſt <hi>What direction have we here touching ſuch good things in particular, as it behoveth us to mention &amp; record, in our thanksgivings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To attend the <note n="t" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 17 18.</note> matter of<note place="margin">Pſal: 71, 14, 16. Eſa. 26. 13 1 Chron: 16. 4.</note> the ſeveral heads of Petition, and ſo to look at the ſame good things, as we are to beg; as the ſame we are to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for. As the cauſall conjunction [For] ſeemes to point out.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherin lyeth the force of that expreſſion [For]?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It ſeemeth to denote this reaſon why we ſhould depend upon God in prayer, for all and every, the ſeverall good things before ſpecified: Namely becauſe, that of God doth appear in each of them (enjoyed) as which ought to be, by the enjoyer, acknowledged to his own prayſe.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:191876:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Where have you any inſtances of any part of the matter; under the firſt head of petitions, acknowledged by way of thankfullnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Pſal. 145. 5, to 21. &amp; 115. 1.<note place="margin">PET. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Where find you inſtances of the matter, under the ſecond head, to this purpoſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Pſal. 146. vers 1. with 7,<note place="margin">PET: 2.</note> to 10. Pſal: 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1, 2, 3. Pſal: 135. &amp; 136 Pſal. 97. &amp; 98. &amp; 99.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where obſerve you any part of the matter of the third, mentioned to Gods prayſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Pſal. 147. 18, 20. Pſal 132.<note place="margin">PET: 3.</note> 15. 1 Theſ: 1, 2. 2 Theſ: 1. 3. Pſal 66. 8, 9. 2 Cor: 9. 13.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where in holy Scripture do you read, of any inſtances of this nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the fourth head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Pſal: 147. 7. &amp; 12, 13, 14.<note place="margin">PET: 4.</note> Pſal: 68. 19. Pſal: 34. 3. Deut: 8 10, 18</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where are there instances of like ſort, pertaining to the fift head?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">PET: 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Pſal: 103. 3, 8, 12 &amp;c: &amp; 85. 2, 3</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhere can you direct me to any inſtance, to the ſame effect, belonging to the ſixt &amp; laſt head of petitions?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:191876:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Pſal: 34. 19, 20. Pſal: 33. 18<note place="margin">PET: 6.</note> 20. Pſal: 30 11. 2 Tim: 4. 17, 18.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not ſufficient unto true thankfullnes, barely to mention before God ſuch of theſe good things, as we profeſs our ſelves thankfull for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for the formal cauſe, and life of our thankſgivings ſeemeth (by our Saviours direction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere) to ly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the feeling and affectionate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of that, of the Eternal Kingdom, and Power and Glory, of God; which is exerciſed about, and declared in and by, any the ſaid good things, and the graunting &amp; continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may we be then directed to, in thoſe words. (Thine is the Kingdom</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If not alwayes explicitly, yet implicitly at leaſt, to affect our hearts thankfully, with thoſe Divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes which ſhine in ſuch a thing. The<note place="margin">Pſal: 92 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ibid 4.</note> Supream influence of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ordering ought concerning it,<note place="margin">Pſal: 94. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the freenes of Gods Grace in conferring it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there ought elſe, wherwith we ſhould affect our hearts herin?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:191876:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The fullnes of the Lords<note place="margin">Pſal: 95. 3. 7</note> right, and Soveraignty over us, now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in ſuch a good thing, or poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note place="margin">Pſal: 115, 1, 2 3.</note> of it. The ſubjection of all ſuch<note place="margin">Pſal: 114. 3, 8</note> inſtruments to him, as would have withſtood it, and dependance of ought<note place="margin">Pſal: 148. tot</note> what ever concurred inſtrumentally to<note place="margin">Pſal: 93. tot:</note> the effecting of it, upon Him: And Laſtly, but not leaſtly, the Kingly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatourſhip of Chriſt, in the conveyance of this grace of the Covenant unto us.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we taught in thoſe words, (and the Power?</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> The hearty-acknowledgment of ſuch a good thing, as we would expreſs our thankfulnes for:</p>
               <p n="1">1. As an effect of that Power in<note place="margin">Rev: 19. 6. Pſal: 111. 6 &amp; 145. 3, 4 Gen: 17. 1.</note> God, which is Infinite &amp; unſearchable, or of that God, which is Omnipotent or Alſufficient.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it is, not only wrought, but<note place="margin">Pſal: 79: 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal: 59. 16 Ephe: 1. 10</note> applyed alſo &amp; continued to us, by the ſaid Power of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As wherby alſo the means, or<note place="margin">Pſal: 145. 11. 1 Pet: 1. 5 Pſal: 66. 3. 7.</note> ſecond cauſes conducing ought therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are &amp; were enabled, to reach their ends, and impediments removed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As whe by we enjoy the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<note place="margin">Ephe: 3. 20.</note>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:191876:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> of it, and are therupon the more<note place="margin">Pſal: 68. 34, 37.</note> fitted and enabled, to the ſervice of our God.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What learn you from thoſe words [And the Glory?</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That what ever Divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,<note place="margin">Ephe: 2. 12. Pſal: 145. 5, 10, 11. 2 Theſ. 1. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal: 111. 3 Rom: 9. 22, 23. Pſal: 96. 8. Pſal: 105. 1, 3</note> ſuch a thing doth ſpeak the glory of, be taken notice of by us, &amp; be acknowledged in ſuch wiſe; as both our hearts be lifted, in the exalting the whole Glory of Gods great &amp; Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name: and others be provoked alſo to ſet forth, and to be affected with, the Glory of God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What gather we from thoſe words [For ever &amp; ever?</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As an acknowledgment of God as the ſame JEHOVAH, from everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. 6. Heb: 13. 8. Rev: 1. 8. 1 Chron: 29 14, 16.</note> to everlaſting, and that we yet owe our ſelves, and all we are &amp; have unto Him: So an avowing, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging our ſelves, and what we have<note place="margin">Gen: 28. 20. 21.</note> unto him through his grace for the future.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the force of that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.</note> 
                  <hi>Concluſive particle [Amen.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> It is an expreſſion, wherby wee both proſeſs that we do &amp; will (through
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:191876:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Grace look after our prayers: And<note place="margin">Pſal: 85. 8. 1 Cor: 14. 16 2 Cor: 1. 20. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et: 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Rev: 3. 14.</note> do teſtify as the fervent deſire, ſo the thankfull perſwaſion of our hearts, of Gods hearing, &amp; accepting our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in and through Him, who is of all his promiſſes (wherof this prayer is a Summary Store-houſe) the AMEN.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="appendix">
               <head>
                  <hi>APPENDIX</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Appendix 2.</note> Second TOUCHING the NATURE<note place="margin">Of the two Sacraments</note> 
                  <hi>And uſe of the two Sacraments of the</hi> GOSPEL.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat neceſſity is there of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</note> 
                  <hi>the Doctrine and uſe of the two Sacraments of the Goſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To remove Ignorance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To prevent Superſtition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To redreſs much unpreparation touching them.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin do the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Goſpel; Baptiſm, and the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:191876:23"/> Lords Supper, and thoſe two of the Law Circumciſion &amp; the Paſſeover ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor: 10. 1 2, 4. Rom. 4. 11. 1 Cor: 5. 7.</note> Subſtance of ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: the ſame Chriſt, Righteouſnes Grace, Life, ſealed up in both.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin do they differ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As in other reſpects, ſo in their <note n="b" place="margin">Gen: 17. 11 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mat: 3. 11. Mat: 26. 19 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ver: 26, 27 Mat: 28. 19. 20. Heb: 2. 2. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 10. 28, 29.</note> Elements of reſemblance Duration and manner of ſignification, and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Thoſe of the Goſpel being more Cleer, powerful, extenſive, and for continuance.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin do Baptiſm, and the Supper agree?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As in ſome other reſpects, ſo in <note n="c" place="margin">Rom: 4. 11 1 Cor: 1. 30 Rom: 6. 3, 6 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 Cor: 10. 16.</note> Repreſenting, exhibiting &amp; ſealing the ſame grace of the Covenant, the ſame Chriſt, the ſame benefits by Chriſt</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVherin do they differ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. In their <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 2. 41. 42.</note> Order, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm preceds, the Supper follows.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In their <note n="e" place="margin">Ephe: 4. 5. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 Cor: 11. 26.</note> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, Baptiſm once, the Supper oft adminiſtred.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In their <note n="f" place="margin">Mat: 3. 11. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 Cor: 11 23. 25.</note> Elements, water belongs to Baptiſm, bread &amp; wine to the Supper.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In their <note n="g" place="margin">Acts 2, 38, 39. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 Cor: 11, 28, 29, 31</note> Subject, Baptiſm includes even Infants, the Supper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:191876:23"/> to grown perſons, in whom is ſome ſettlement of judgment, &amp; ſcund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of affection.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In their <note n="h" place="margin">Gal: 3. 27. with Rev: 3, 20.</note> Uſe, Baptiſm doth point out a Being in Chriſt, and in the Covenant: The Supper, a continuance and growth therin.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What conſiderations doth the outward matter of the Elements offer to us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe two eſpecially.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Senciblenes of them, point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Wiſdom &amp; Love of Chriſt, in applying himſelf to divers ſences at once; the more familiarly to convey the Savour of himſelf to us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor: 2. 5. &amp; 14.</note> Simplicity of them, as which be more generally, and eaſily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable, and more ſafe &amp; intire from carnal ſenſuallity &amp; pomp.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the formal excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of theſe Ordinances, or wherin doth it conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the due <note n="k" place="margin">Mat: 3. 11 Rom: 6. 3. 4 1 Cor: 11. 24</note> appropriation, of the outward Elements &amp; ſignes to, and their union with the grace ſignified</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the general end, and uſe of theſe two Seals?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:191876:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Sealing or ratifying the whole Covenant: The promiſory part on Gods part to us ward: the reſtipulatory or repromiſory part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of on our parts to God-ward. In ſum, That He will be our <note n="l" place="margin">Gen: 17. 1, 10.</note> God, and we will be (through the Grace of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant) his people.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſubordinate end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="m" place="margin">Gen: 17. 13 1 Cor: 10. 16, 17.</note> profeſſion of our faith and charity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherin doth the Lord aſſure us thereby, that he will be our God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In exhibiting his <note n="n" place="margin">Rom: 8. 32 2 Cor: 1. 20.</note> Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, with all his benefits, in all their fulnes: and in all the dimenſions, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp; treaſures, of breeding, or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing grace.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVe having thus looked into the Conſtitution of theſe Sacraments, Let us ſee what pertayns to the due Celebration of them in general?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A <note n="o" place="margin">Heb: 5. 4 Ephe: 3, 2, 4. 1 Tim: 3. 2 Eſay 52. 11. Hag: 2. 12. Pſal: 50. 21. Exod: 12 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mat: 3. 11. 1 Cor: 11. 24 28.</note> Miniſter, &amp; people duely qualified, and the Sacramental acts duely attended, according to Chriſts inſtitution.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whoſe place doth the Minister ſuſtein in theſe acts?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:191876:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The place of Chriſts <note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor: 5. 20 1 Cor. 4. 1.</note> Embaſſadour, and the Steward of the Myſteries of God.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What be thoſe Sacramentall acts, and what is their uſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Waſhing <note n="q" place="margin">Mat: 3. 5 Mat: 26. 26, 27.</note> or ſprinkling breaking, pouring forth, diſtributing, taking, eating, drinking, &amp;c: which ſerve to ſet forth the application and reception of the Grace repreſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Elements.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why uſe you Baptiſm, in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In particular</note> 
                  <hi>the firſt place?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not only <note n="q" place="margin">Mat: 21. 25 Exod: 12. 48 Col: 2. 11, 12</note> becauſe it was<note place="margin">Of Baptiſm.</note> firſt ordayned (as was alſo Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to which it anſwers in ſubſtance of reſemblance) But becauſe in order of nature, our planting or ingraffing into Chriſt, and our begetting, breeding &amp;<note place="margin">Rom: 11, 17. Pſal: 1. 3. Pſal: 87. 5, 6</note> bringing forth of the womb of the Church, do precede our nouriſhment and growth therin.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Parents duty, in reſpect of the Infant to be Baptiſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="r" place="margin">Mat: 23. 28 Mat: 19. 13. Pſal: 51. 4. 2 Sam: 12. 16 23.</note> preſent it to the Lord in this Ordinance of his in due ſeaſon, in the face of the publike Aſſembly: And in the due conſideration of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:191876:25"/> woefull pollution of nature, conveyed by them unto it, to commiſerate it in<note place="margin">Exod: 20. 6. Gen: 17 7.</note> their ſouls, mourn &amp; ſign for it, and to revive their faith in the Covenant, as touching their ſeed.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is this all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Further, they are to <note n="s" place="margin">Mat: 3. 11. 1 Cor: 7. 17. Epheſ: 2. 11, 12. Ephe: 6. 4.</note> joyn with the Church in humble confeſſion of its original guilt, Supplication for the inward &amp; ſpiritual waſhing, and thankſ-giving for ſuch a means of ſtrengthning their faith, as touching Gods good-will toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it: and ſo to give it up unto the Lord, and to his people in him, devoting it to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, &amp; engaging the bringing it up to him, and for him.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Churches duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As each one for his part, to call to mind, the grace of <note n="t" place="margin">1 Pet: 3. 21. Mark 16. 16 1 Cor: 15. 29 Gal: 3. 27. Rom: 6. 3. Mat: 28, 19</note> Baptiſm, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly offered to him, to abaſe himſelf in the ſenſe of the former breach of his engagement, and Reverently to attend this Ordinance, improving the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his own Baptiſm to his own ſpiritual advantage: So all of them joyntly, by humble confeſſion, prayer, and thankſ-giving to look up unto
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:191876:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> God for the Infant (or who other) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Miniſters duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to underſtand ſo to teach<note place="margin">2 Cor: 3. 6. Mat: 28. 27. Exod: 40. 9 Mat: 3. 11. 1 Tim: 4. 4. &amp; 3. 15.</note> the doctrine &amp; uſe of this Ordinance, and in a grave, holy ſort to diſpence the ſame, according to the Inſtitution, with prayer, and thankſ-giving.</p>
               <p>Queſt <hi>How can Infants be conceived capable of Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As well, as of <note n="u" place="margin">Col: 2. 11, 12. with 1 Cor. 7. 14. 1 Pet: 3. 21. Deut: 30. 6 Ephe: 2. 5.</note> Circumciſion of old. And to be Baptiſed, or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, outwardly, or inwardly, no external action of the receiver is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily pre-required, he being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly rather a patient therin: and alſo there being no word in the new Teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,<note place="margin">Gen: 17. 11, 12.</note> which makes void that former appointment of God, of ſetting the initiating Seal of the Covenant upon ſuch.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>To what uſe ſerves it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="w" place="margin">Gal: 6. 10 1 Cor: 12. 13 John 15: 2 Rom: 4. 11 Gen: 17. 11. Heb: 12. 25</note> Signify, and ſeal, its viſible relation to Chriſt his body the Church; and unto Chriſt himſelf, the head of his Church, by vertue of the Covenant: and conſequently its viſible intereſt, in the Priviledges of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:191876:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; its obligation to the termes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and conditions of it.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat things are there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords Supper.</note> 
                  <hi>conſiderable in the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Principally. 1. The out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Elements and actions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The inward diſtinct grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſpecial end of it.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why are here two diſtinct E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, and in Baptiſm but one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe, this Ordinance tends to <note n="x" place="margin">Eſay 4. 16 Pſal: 104. 15. Judg: 19. 19 Rom: 14. 21.</note> ſet forth the full nouriſhment of the ſoul: and this neither bread, nor wine apart would do, the one being the ſtaff of Life, the other the cheriſher of the ſpirits.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we to obſerve, as touching the outward acts of the Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The acts on the Miniſters part and on the receivers.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the acts on the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters part?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe four. To <note n="y" place="margin">Luke 22. 10. 20. 1 Cor: 11. 23 24:</note> Take, To Bleſs, To Break or poure out, and to deliver forth the Elements in the Name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What do theſe actions import?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſetting of Chriſt apart for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:191876:26"/> ſuffering, and death and ſuffering of<note place="margin">Acts 2. 23, 36 1 Cor: 21. 26 John 6. 51</note> Chriſt accordingly, and the free com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the benefits therof to ſo many as do receive him.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Whence is it, that from Chriſt is our ſpiritual ſupport, and ſtrength in grace, as well as our firſt being in grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> From hence, that He is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed<note place="margin">
                     <hi>a</hi> Heb: 9. 15 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n: 2. 5. 2 Cor: 1. 20 Col: 3. 11 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: 2, 10. John 10. 10.</note> &amp; hath undertaken to be the alone Mediatour of the Covenant, and ſo the All in all of the ſouls-happines.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How is Chriſt propounded to us in the Supper, as the ſoul-nouriſhment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As the ſame <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor: 11. 24 1 Cor: 10: 16</note> ſtands in relation to the word of promiſe, wherin Chriſt is made the ſouls own, to feed her</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin doth the Sacramentall nouriſhment ſtand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In all <note n="c" place="margin">2 Pet: 1. 3. Pſal: 84. 11 &amp; 37. 4 &amp; 92 12, 13, 14. Hoſ: 14. 5. 8 3 John 2 John 1: 17: &amp; 17. 11 Eſay 63. 3, 4. Ephe: 4. 16 Pſal: 73. 26 1 Cor: 15. 58.</note> manner of Spiritual ſupply, to any of the wants of the ſoul as concerns its health, growth, ſtability or fruitfulnes in grace.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What do thoſe acts of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, in taking, eating &amp; drinking, the Elements ſet forth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How Faith-Sacramental <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 1. 29. Luke 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eſay 25. 6, 7, 3. Pſal: 118. 24. Eſa. 55. 2</note> apprehends &amp; applies Chriſt, al-along to the ſoules ſpiritual nouriſhment:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:191876:27"/> For it conſenting to the word of Gods<note place="margin">Tit: 1. 15. Rev: 3. 16. Jer: 2. 13:</note> promiſe &amp; tender, &amp; ſubmitting in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his command, does lay hold upon &amp; improue Chriſt, to all needful ſupplies of Grace, ſpiritual ſtrength, &amp; life, and gathers out the ſweetnes and comfort of all.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the end &amp; uſe of the Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To confirm <note n="e" place="margin">John 10. 9 &amp; 15. 4. Heb: 9. 16.</note> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, concerning nouriſhment and growth by Chriſt, to the experience of the believing ſoul, depending alone upon Chriſt, and his grace for the ſame</p>
               <p>2. To <note n="f" place="margin">Col: 2. 20 2 Cor: 5. 14, 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor: 11. 16</note> engage the ſoul, both to depend conſtantly &amp; confidently upon Chriſt to that end for the future and to improve all back again unto Chriſt, and his Honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="appendix">
               <head>
                  <hi>APPENDIX</hi> third TOUCHING OBEDIENCE<note place="margin">Appendix 3. of the Decalogue.</note> 
                  <hi>And the Rule thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:191876:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E having (in part) diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what God will do for us: Now let us hear what Hee requireth of us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Obedience unto <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal: 40. 8. Pſal: 143. 10. Mat: 7. 21.</note> his Will Revealed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where is Gods Will made known?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the <note n="b" place="margin">Mat: 22. 40. 2 Tim: 3. 16. 17.</note> holy Scriptures, of the Prophets and Apoſtles, whereby the Moral-Law (which is an Abbreviat of Gods Will) is in the ſeveral parts of it fully explained.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Moral-Law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is that <note n="c" place="margin">Pſa: 19. 7, 10 Exod. 16. &amp; 17. 1. &amp; 19. 2 &amp; 19. 9 with Exod: 20. 1-Eccl: 12. 13 1 Cor: 10. 2. 3 &amp; Ex: 31. 18</note> full, perfect &amp; unchangable Rule, which the Lord himſelf gave &amp; uttered, as his laſt will, unto his people in the wildernes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the whole duty of thankfullnes and obedience; which the Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ones in Covenant with Him, be obliged unto.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many things do you obſerve in it, as you have it expreſsed in</hi> Exod: 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Preface, verſe 1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements themſelves to verſe 17.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Whereto ſerves the Preface?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:191876:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To acquaint us with a three fold reaſon enforcing the obedience to this Law, upon the Lords people.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe, He is <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 49. 5. 9 Pſal: 45. 11.</note> the Lord, having Soveraign Dominion over all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe, He is our <note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor: 7. 1 2 Pet: 1. 4</note> Covenant-God, all the Promiſes wherof, are ſo many engagements unto obedience.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the third reaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe of the ſeveral engaging <note n="f" place="margin">Luke 1. 74. Eph 4. 20, 21 Eſay 43. 1, 2, 3.</note> Mercies, which we do partake in, by vertue of the Couenant: and as the Head of all, Our Redemption by Chriſt, figured by that deliverance the Church had out of Egypt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is the Moral-Law divided?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into ten <note n="g" place="margin">Exo: 34, 18 Exod: 32. 15 Mat: 22, 26, 27.</note> Commandents or Words, conteined under two Tables. The firſt Table conſiſts of the four firſt concerning the duty we owe immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God. The ſecond, of the ſix laſt concerning the duty we owe immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our Neighbour.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the general duty of the firſt Table?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="h" place="margin">Mat: 22, 29.</note> Love the Lord thy God with all thy heart &amp;c:</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How may the four firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:191876:28"/> be diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The two firſt concern the matter of worſhip, <hi>viz:</hi> The firſt Natural: as which the knowledg of God and of his Nature teacheth.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, Inſtituted, as which the knowledg of Gods Will teacheth.</p>
               <p>2. The two latter, the adjuncts of Worſhip, <hi>viz:</hi> The third, the holy manner of Worſhip. The fourth the holy time of Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why be ſome Commandments ſet down, in the Affirmative, ſome in the Negative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To point out wherin the <note n="i" place="margin">Hoſea 4. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, 6. &amp; 5. 15.</note> danger of Gods own people, by reaſon of temptation &amp;c: doth nextly, and moſt immediately ly.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is to be obſerved for the better underſtanding of theſe Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Eſpecially four things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Where any Duty is Commanded the contrary evill is forbidden: and contrarywiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Under one particular mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are conteined all of the ſame kind.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Under what ever Duty, or Sin
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:191876:29"/> expreſſed, all both meanes, occaſions, &amp; ſignes therof are intended.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Under Man, of whom duty is required, the whole Nature of man, and under one Relation, all ſorts of relation, are comprehended.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt HAVE no other <note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 20. 3</note> GOD before ME.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is required in Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment first?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That we do <note n="l" place="margin">Eſay 33. 12. Jer. 10. 10 1 Cor: 8, 6</note> enjoy, &amp; own the Lord JEHOVAH, and him alone for our GOD.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is required herunto?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our Spiritual <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal: 4. 6. 1 John 1. 3 Rom: 6. 11</note> Communion with God, both in receiving all Grace from him, and in improving all grace to him, and his Glory.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What ſpecial Graces are they, the enjoyment &amp; improvement wherof is here required?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Knowledg, <note n="n" place="margin">Job 22. 21. 2 Pet: 3. 18</note> Faith, Fear of God, Hope, Love, Humility, Patience Joy in God &amp;c: namely in reſpect of their Being, and Growth.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is required. as wherin to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:191876:29"/> exerciſe theſe graces?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The <note n="o" place="margin">Heb: 3. 7. Mic: 6, 9. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Heb: 4. 2</note> hearing the voyce of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The calling upon his <note n="p" place="margin">Rev. 10. 12 14. 1 Tim: 2 22. Act. 2. 21 Dan: 9. 2, 3 Eſt. 9. 19. Pro: 16. 33. Gen: 28. 20</note> Name in prayer, both ordinarily &amp; extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, with holy faſting or feaſting, or in a religious oath, lot, or vow.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſubmitting to the <note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet: 4. 19 James 1. 23</note> Will of God revealed, both to do &amp; ſuffer, according therunto.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is ought elſe required as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns our Communion with God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, the <note n="r" place="margin">2 Pet: 2. 11 1 John 1. 3, 5 Pſal: 84. 2. &amp; 73. 17.</note> maintaining &amp; improving our Spiritual Communion with Him.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>In what manner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In all <note n="s" place="margin">Num: 14. 24. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 King 18. 21. Num: 25. 12. 13 Mic: 6. 8 Acts 23. 1. &amp; Heb: 10. 22</note> Sincerity, Zeal, Humility, good Conſcience, Watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; Perſevera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. 1 <hi>Pet: 5. 8. Eph:</hi> 6. 18</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>By what means is it maintained?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We are required to that end, to keep in <note n="t" place="margin">Heb: 12. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 Pet: 4. 10 Pſal: 66. 28 2 Pet: 1. 11. Mat. 25. 15</note> high eſteem, carefully to conſerve &amp; encreaſe; and as carefully to improve to Gods honour in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip &amp; ſervice, every gift &amp; grace, of his Spirit in us.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are they that ſo eye this Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement, as to do therafter?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:191876:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such as <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal: 119. 57. Eſay 60. 19 2 Cor: 10. 17</note> take the Lord, to be their only Portion &amp; Glory.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is here require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the uſing ſuch good gifts in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, to his honour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="w" place="margin">2 Chron: 30. 8. Pro: 23. 26. Rom: 13. 10. &amp; Pſal: 16. 1 Eſay 26. 4 Jer: 14. 8 Pro: 23. 17 Rom: 6. 13 Pſal: 116. 9</note> giving up of, both our hearts unto God, in faſtning al our love, truſt, hope &amp; fear upon Him: And alſo our lives, through a care of walking with God whileſt we live.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is required to the improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Communion with God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="x" place="margin">John 7. 17 Rev: 3 20 1 John. 3. 27 John 14. 21, 23.</note> ready ſubjecting our own wills, &amp; endeavours to Gods will and way wholly, and in every reſpect</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>That which we have ſpoken to; appertains to the affirm: part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: what is therefore forbidden in the Negative?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All thoſe motions, vices, and corruptions of heart &amp; life: as which be contrary to the vertues, graces, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, diſpoſitions and duties here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhich is the Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt not <note n="y" place="margin">Exod: 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4 5 6.</note> MAKE to thy ſelf, any GRAVEN Image &amp;c:</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:191876:30"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we to take notice of, as contained in this Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. What is therin Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded.</p>
               <p>2. The Reaſons in particular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing it.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How may we gather what is herein Commanded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> From the contrary herein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden, according as in the former.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is in generall here forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="z" place="margin">Jer: 7. 31. Acts 24. 14.</note> Worſhiping of God, with ſuch outward Worſhip, as hath not Him the Author therof.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then required here?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="a" place="margin">Deut: 12. 32 &amp; 4 12. Mat: 28. 20.</note> Worſhip God, with ſuch outward Worſhip, as only him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath appointed, and in his Word revealed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat outward worſhip, hath the Lord appointed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="b" place="margin">1 Tim: 3. 16 John 5. 39 &amp; Col: 3. 16 Luke 4. 21. Acts 2. &amp; 3. &amp; 7. Pro: 22. 6. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gal: 6. 6.</note> exerciſe &amp; uſe of the holy Scriptures, both in publick, and in private; by the inſtant attendance upon the reading, preaching, or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therof, even in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:191876:31"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Meditation <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal: 1. 2. Mat: 26, 30. Col: 3. 16 Mat: 3. 16 Luke 24. 14. 2 Tim: 4. 2</note> therupon, ſinging of Pſalmes, and holy confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, tending to mutual edification.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What elſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="d" place="margin">Phil: 4. 6. Acts 3. 2 &amp; Mat: 21. 13 Pro: 3. 6. &amp; 20. 24 Zech: 12 12 14. Joſh: 24. 15. Mat: 6. 6.</note> uſe and exerciſe of Prayer, in our publick meetings, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious &amp; Civil: in our private families dayly, &amp; continually, and in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret retirements oft, and upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other means of worſhip is there?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor: 4. 17 Pſal: 2. 12 Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. 19 Acts 14. 23 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Tit: 1. 5 &amp; 1 Cor: 5. 13 Phil: 1. 1 Mat: 18. 16, 17 Act: 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7 Acts 20. 28 1 Cor: 12. 25</note> Ordinances of the Goſpel, which peculiarly doe reſpect a particular viſible Church, both its conſtitution, and its ſtate being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, its Inorganick, and its Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick ſtate: And laſtly alſo ſuch as concern either the whole Church joyntly, or the members in particular.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the uſe of Seals and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures included?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the ſame are <note n="f" place="margin">Mat: 28. 18. Acts 2. 44 Mat: 18. 17 2 Cor: 2. 6, 7</note> amongſt other Ordinances, enjoyned here.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What appears to be here parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly forbidden?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As all <note n="g" place="margin">Deut: 4. 2 Mat: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 8, 9</note> humane inventions &amp;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:191876:31"/> appointments in Gods Worſhip: So<note place="margin">James 4. 2. Luke 19. 27. Rev: 3. 9 Gal: 2. 4 Luke 13. 34. Zech: 14. 16 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Zeph: 3. 11 1 Sam: 4 3 w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Jer: 7. 4, 14. Lam: 4. 20 Act. 14. 12, 14 1 Cor: 1. 12 Amos 5. 16 1 King. 22. 43.</note> all profane contempt, or careleſs neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, of any part of Gods outward Worſhip, appointed by himſelf.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is there ought elſe here forbidden</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, the Superſtitious abuſe or Idolizing any of the Inſtruments, or meanes appointed of God, in his Worſhip: and the doing of any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to any humane device.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat are the Reaſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are two.</p>
               <p>The firſt is taken from the Juſtice of <note n="i" place="margin">Deut: 23. 8. Exod: 34. 7 Num: 14. 18 Mat: 3. 7 Luke 13. 35.</note> God in avenging the breach of this Commandement, upon the offender, and his poſterity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond Reaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is taken from the <note n="k" place="margin">Deut: 5. 29. &amp; 12. 25, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal: 112. 2 Deut: 30. 6 Acts 2. 39 2 Cor: 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4 John 14. 15</note> Mercy of God extended, in ſuch the fruits of it, as are the viſible tokens of his favour &amp; preſence, in his Ordinances; to the keepers of this Law, and their Ofspring, who are here looked at, as ſuch as Love God; when the breakers are ſuch as hate him.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the third Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the Name<note place="margin">Exod: 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:191876:32"/> of God in VAIN &amp;c:</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How many things are obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Commandement it ſelf. 2. The Reaſons of it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it to take Gods Name in vain?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In thought, word, or deed to abuſe, or profane the Name of God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is to be underſtood by the Name of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All what ever relates unto God as his <note n="l" place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 15 Exod: 33. 19 Deut: 32, 3 Deut: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5 2 Chron: 7. 14. Rom: 1. 19, 20.</note> Worſhip, and the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Him, his Church, his Word, Ordinances &amp; Works; as well as his Titles, and Attributes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then the Scope of this third Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To Regulate all the worſhipers of God in the right manner of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him, and in the right uſe of all that is called his Name, and alſo in the ordering their own converſation aright</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>In what manner ought wee to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> 
                  <hi>worſhip God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In [<hi>m</hi>] Spirit and in Truth.<note place="margin">John 4. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But after what manner, more particularly?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:191876:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ought to <note n="n" place="margin">Job 23. 12. Pſal: 84. 12. Pro: 23. 13 Mat: 13. 44. Pro: 8. 34 1 Pet: 2. 2 Pſal: 42. 2, 4 Pſal: 122. 1. &amp; 69. 9. 2 Chr. 12. 12 1 Cor: 14. 20</note> apply our ſelves to the holy Worſhip of God, with a holy deſire, affection, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, Before; With due Reverence, and Devotion, In; and with a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſavour and uſe of it, After: All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes obſerving outward Order, and Decency, in &amp; about the ſame. <hi>Ec. 5. 1, 2 Heb: 12. 28. Lev: 19. 30. Act. 10. 2. Pſal: 18. 1. Cant: 2. 3. Heb: 4. 2. 1 Theſ.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
               <p>Queſt <hi>How ſhould we uſe the Titles</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Titles.</note> 
                  <hi>of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In <note n="o" place="margin">1 Pet: 3. 15. Eccleſ: 5. 2 Gen: 14 19 Jer: 4. 2.</note> ſerious matters, after a Reverent manner, and to a good end, holding them forth in a holy life. <hi>Rom 9. 5. 1 Cor: 10. 31. 1 Theſ.</hi> 1. 12. &amp; 2. 12</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How ſhould wee uſe his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Attributs</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In ſuch a <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 104. 34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal: 139. 17. Rom: 2. 4 Joel 2. 14 Pro: 16. 10 Rom: 4. 20 Gen: 17. 1 Rom: 12. 1 2 Sam: 16. 10 Jer: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 6, 7</note> holy ſort to acquaint our ſelves with them, and to think, and ſpeak of them, as to the gaining ſome ſpiritual ſweetnes, ſavour and fruit thereby. <hi>Exo: 15. 11. Pſa.</hi> 31. 7</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How ſhould we demean our ſelves towards Gods Church, and thoſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. Church</note> 
                  <hi>in Covenant with Him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal: 16. 3 &amp; 15. 4. Pſal 137. 6. Col. 1. 4. 1 Joh: 3. 14</note> prize, honour, &amp; love ſuch, to entertain &amp; deſire fellowſhip
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:191876:33"/> with them, imitate their vertues, help<note place="margin">Pſal. 122. 6, 9 Pro: 15. 12 &amp; 13. 20. Acts 9. 26 &amp; 21. 7 Heb: 6: 12 &amp; 13. 7 Gal. 6. 10.</note> bear their burdens, ſympathize with them in their conditions, ſeek their prayers for us, &amp; long after their good all our dayes. <hi>Pro: 20. 4. Rom, 12. 15. Gal: 6. 2. 2 Theſ: 1. 11. 1 Theſ:</hi> 5. 25.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How are we to Sanctifie the Name of God in his Workes?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. Works.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In the beholding the <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal: 143. 5, 6. Eſay 51. 6 Heb: 1. 10. Pſal: 105. 2, 3 Rom: 1. 19, 21.</note>
                  <note place="margin">1. of Creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> works of Creation, to ſee that our hearts be drawn neerer to himſelf the Creatour, our Tongues do utter his Prayſes, and our Lives do ſpeak a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual uſe made of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In <note n="s" place="margin">Afflicting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal: 32. 4 &amp; 38. 2. Mic: 6. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am: 3. 39. Deut: 8. 2. Eſay 30. 15 Pſal: 131. 5</note> Afflicting Providences,<note place="margin">2. of Provid.</note> to ſee and acknowledg Gods handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, to ſearch out his mind, and to be quickned thereby, unto Humiliation Repentance, Dependance upon God, Weanednes from the world, &amp; the like.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the <note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim: 4. 5. Jude ver: 12 Rom: 14. 23. Gen: 32. 10. 1 Cor: 10. 31 Pro: 3. 7. Amos 6. 6 1 Tim: 6. 17 18, 19. Luke 21. 34, 36.</note> plentifull Supply of<note place="margin">2. Smiling.</note> the Creature, to receive it thankfully from God the giver, and to uſe it in all holy fear, faith, humility, zeal of Gods Glory, and care of others good: with watchfulnes, ſobriety, and the minding our latter end. 1 <hi>Pet: 5. 8. Pſal:</hi> 30. 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To obſerve, admire, &amp; magnifie<note place="margin">3. of Grace.</note>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:191876:33"/> the works of his Grace, upon whom-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever:<note place="margin">Rom: 11. 33. Ephe: 1. 7 2 John 4. 1 Pet: 5. 10 Pſal: 66. 16 2 Pet: 1. 8 &amp; 3. 18. &amp; Eph: 4. 1 Coloſ: 2. 19</note> to rejoyce therat, to ſeek the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting therof; and readily to ſhew forth what God hath done for us that way, to the Glory of God, and the edification of others: and to walk worthy of his Grace, depending upon him for dayly freſt ſupply.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the particular miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, tending to the breach of this Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are the ſeveral evills, as conſiſt either in the <note n="w" place="margin">1 Chron: 15. 13. Mat: 15. 9.</note> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect of any the graces or duties preſcribed, or in what-ever is in conrariety thereto.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Whereto ſerves the Reaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To teach us, <note n="x" place="margin">Hoſea 4. 1. Jer: 23. 10, 11, 12. Jer: 7 18 Zech: 5. 4 1 Chr: 15. 15 1 King: 13. 4 Acts 5. 5. 2 King: 19. 22, 35 1 Cor: 11. 30</note> that though man fayles, yet God never failes, even manifeſtly to puniſh the wilfull breach of this Commandement.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Command: 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw?</hi> Remember thou keep <note n="y" place="margin">Exod: 20. 8 to 11.</note> Holy the SABBATH day &amp;c:</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What things are here to bee taken notice of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Dutyes enjoyned.</p>
               <p>2. The Reaſons preſſing to them.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:191876:34"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the general duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Solemnly &amp; Religiouſly to obſerve, a certain ſet ſolemn time, of the Lords own appointment, for the drawing neerer to himſelf, in all the wayes of his holy Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that ſet time of Gods own appointment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is the <note n="z" place="margin">Mat: 24. 20 Eſay 56. 6. Eſay 58. 13. Rev: 1. 6.</note> ſeaventh part of time, or ſeaventh Day, called the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, or particularly the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, or the Lords-day.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Hath the Lord left us any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Rule, whereby to find out the time, of the begining &amp; end of the Sabbath?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The firſt ſeaventh day from the <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 2. 2, 3 Exod: 31. 17</note> Creation, wherin the Lord reſted from all his works, which he Created, is laid before us in this Commandment as a pattern-Sabbath, guiding us as in other reſpects, ſo in this of the time, wherin we ought to begin and end out Sabbath.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why obſerve we the firſt day of the week, ſeing the ſeaventh or laſt day was at firſt obſerved in the Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The day is by <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 118. 24 John 20. 19, 26. Act. 2. 1. &amp;c:</note> Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment now changed, from the laſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:191876:34"/> day of the week to the firſt, for the<note place="margin">Lev: 23. 11, 16. Acts 20. 17. 1 Cor: 16 2. Rev: 1. 10.</note> memorial of the Lord Chriſt his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as upon this Day.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Sabbath-duty in particular?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To Reſt this day.</p>
               <p>2. To Sanctifie the ſame.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are we enjoyned to Reſt from, upon this Day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not only from the breach of <note n="c" place="margin">Lev: 23. 7. Eſay 58. 13 Exod: 16. 28 29. Luke 23. 56. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mark 16. 1. Exod: 31. 13 &amp; 24. 21. Neh. 13. 16, 20 Jer: 17. 24. Exod: 16. 9</note> any other Commandement, which is euery-dayes-duty: but from occupying our ſelves about ſuch things as are lawfull upon an other day, attended to.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But is this Rest abſolutely enjoyned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw,</hi> No, for what <note n="d" place="margin">Mat: 12. 1, 9 2 King: 4. 23 Pſal: 81. 3. Neh: 8. 10 Neh: 5. 18.</note> tends to further the Worſhip of God on the day, or elſe doth appertain to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon honeſty, or to the ſerving ſome ſpecial Divine Providence, impoſing a neceſſity of preſent labour, for the preſervation of life, or the comfort of it: the ſame may be done on this day.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is it to keep it Holy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To paſs the time holily, in the holy attendance upon the duties of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:191876:35"/> Gods holy Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe dutyes of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip wherin we are to imploy our ſelves on this day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All thoſe <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> tot &amp; 63: &amp; 27 4. Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7 2 Tim. 4. 2 Acts 16. 13. Ezek: 46. 1, 01.</note> which are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in firſt &amp; ſecond Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement in that manner of wiſe as required in the third, and this in publick &amp; in private.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is that which is commonly called Contribution, a publick Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes work?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As (in the <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 21. 1. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 Cor: 16 1, 2. Exod: 23. 15 Pſal: 45. 12. Mat: 5. 23.</note> due performance of it,) it is a fruit of faith &amp; holines an act of love &amp; mercy, a teſtimony of thankfulnes, and a token of a heart enla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged in the ſenſe of Gods bounty, on that day taſted of, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced in: ſo it is moſt ſuitable to the publick work of the day.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the private dutyes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as we are to attend before the publick or after, either in the family, or a part by our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be they that be to go before?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <note n="g" place="margin">Num 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10: Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 119 147, 148: Pſal: 63. 1.</note> reading Gods word, &amp; inſtructing the family there-from, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, holy meditation of Gods word and works &amp;c:</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:191876:35"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What be they that be to follow?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Meditation <note n="h" place="margin">Mal: 2. 2 Luke 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9. Pſal: 119. 97. 98. Acts 17. 11 Deut: 6. 6 Heb: 2. 2. Acts 13. 42 Luke 24. 17. Num: 28. 10. Pſal. 92. 1, 2.</note> of the word heard, examination of what was taught by the word, recalling it over in the family, taking triall of their profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who are under our charge, holy conference, prayer, ſinging of pſalms.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To whom is this charge concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſanctifying of the Sabbath given?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As the charge <note n="i" place="margin">Neh: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 15 1 Tim: 2. 2. Jer. 17. 20, 27 Gen: 18. 19 Pſal: 101. 8. Joſh 24. 13 2 Chron: 34. 33.</note> concerns all, So in an eſpecial ſort ſuch as are Superiours, as to keep it themſelves, ſo to care that they who be under them, do ſo alſo.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What be the Reaſons uſed here to enforce the care of ſanctifying the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> There be divers reaſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated, but three mainly inſiſted upon</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt wherof is taken from the equity of the Command.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond from Gods own example.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From the Divine inſtitution of the day, and his bleſſing it to the ſincere obſervers of it.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the duty in generall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond Table.</note> 
                  <hi>which the ſecond Table enjoynes?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:191876:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To love our <note n="k" place="margin">Mat: 22: 39</note> neighbour as our ſelve.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto what special heads are the dutyes of Love or Righteouſnes which we owe unto our neighbour to be referred according to the order of the ſix following Commandements belonging unto the ſecond Table?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto theſe ſix heads.</p>
               <p>The firſt concerns our Neighbours Honour &amp; eſtimation.</p>
               <p>The ſecond his life &amp; lively-hood</p>
               <p>The third his chaſtity &amp; purity.</p>
               <p>The fourth his outward eſtate and goods.</p>
               <p>The fift &amp; ſixt, as in order to the better performance of our charge reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the foregoing, enjoynes us</p>
               <p n="1">1. Truth in our speeches, promiſes and dealings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Contentation, with our own condition.<note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the fift Commandment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> HONOUR thy Father &amp;c:<note place="margin">Exod: 20. 12</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What conſider you in it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Precept it ſelfe, and the<note place="margin">Epheſ: 6. 2</note> Promiſe annexed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Scope of that Precept?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:191876:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To direct <note n="m" place="margin">Eccl: 10. 7 Gen: 2. 10 Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: 4. 9 Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: 133. 1: 1 Cor: 14. 40</note> as a Rule, each one of us in that his duty, to be performed to his neighbour, which his Place, Age, or gifts properly call for: as to the end Political-order might by this means be duely obſerved in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane-Societyes, warranted by God.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Why are the duties due from all ſorts of relations, in humane-ſocieties preſcribed under the term of Honour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the duty which ones <note n="n" place="margin">1 Pet: 2. 17 &amp; 3. 7. Pro: 29. 15 Eccl: 4. 13</note> place, or condit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on calls for from an other, doth in the due performance of it, and ought in the doing thereof to reſpect his Honour, whether he be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, equal, or inferiour.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is that duty of Honour which we do owe in general to all, whether Superiours, equalls, or inferiours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To tender, &amp; <note n="o" place="margin">Rom: 12. 10 1 Pet: 2. 17 1 Sam: 19. 4 Mat: 18. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. Pro: 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour according to Rule, the uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſtate of worth, excellency, or reputation of our neighbour, with which God hath inveſted him in any humane ſociety; and not only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it un-impaired, and unblemiſhed but even to promote the ſame, ſo far forth as in us lyeth.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:191876:37"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the duty in general, which we are here enjoyned to perform to our Superiours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Both <note n="p" place="margin">Lev: 19. 3 1 King. 1. 17 24. John 20 15. Mat. 13. 27. Job 32. 4 &amp; 29. 7, 10. Lev: 19. 32 1 King: 2. 19 Gen: 43. 23 Rom: 13. 6, 7 1 Pet: 3. 3 1 Sam: 15. 30 with 2 Sam: 20. 1, 2.</note> inwardly to Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them in our hearts, and outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in due ſort to expreſs the ſame, and that readily upon all occaſions, both in word &amp; deed, in ſuch wiſe as may both teſtifie our eſteem of them, as our betters, and our care to deſerve well of them; yea and to procure likewiſe unto them like honourable eſteem &amp; reſpect from others.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What on the other ſide is the duty we as Superiours, do owe unto our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal: 27. 10 &amp; 103. 13, 14 Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y 49. 15 Pro: 2. 12. 1 Theſ 2. 11 Job 31 18 &amp; 29. 16. Gen 43 29, 30 1 Sam: 3. 6. 2 Cor. 6. 13 R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th 3. 10, 11, &amp; 2. 8</note> bear and maintain to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, an inward Parental-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, and ſuitably to demean our ſelves in ſpeech &amp; action. 1 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. 3. 7. Tit</hi> 2. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the dutyes the Huſband and the wife do mutually owe each to other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Conjugal-love, <note n="r" place="margin">Ephe: 5. 25 Titus 2 4 Pto: 5. 19 Mal: 2. 14. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pro: 2. 17. &amp; 31, 11. &amp; 12. 13. &amp; 12. 4.</note> faithfulnes, helpfulnes,, and alſo fellowſhip in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily worſhip. <hi>Gen. 2. 18. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ei.</hi> 3. 7.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be the dutyes which the wife oweth to her huſband?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:191876:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beſides <note n="s" place="margin">Eph: 5. 33. 1 Pet: 3. 2, 4, 5, 6. 3 Tim: 2. 12 Eph: 5. 24</note> the common dutyes aforeſaid, ſhee owes him Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſubjection &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 24</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What be the dutyes of Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the Huſband owes to his wife?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beſides <note n="t" place="margin">Eph: 5. 23. 1 Pet: 3. 5 1 Cor: 14. 34 35. Eph: 5. 29 Exod: 21. 10 1 Tim: 5. 8.</note> the common duties before mentioned, he as a head ſhould care to govern, direct, protect and cheriſh her, as a part of himſelf, and to provide for her, to his beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, according to his place and condition.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What be the duties of Honour that children do owe unto their natural Parents?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">1 Tim: 5. 4. Gen: 42. 12 Mark 7. 11 Gen: 5. 29 Pro: 23. 24, 25 Ruth 4. 15 Gen: 25. 9 Gen: 48. 12 Col: 3. 20.</note> Thankful-Recompence due-Reverence, and child-like-Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But be the ſame dutyes due to step-fathers &amp; step-mothers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, in as much as <note n="w" place="margin">Ruth 2. 11 18. &amp; 3. 5. &amp; 2 2. &amp; 3. 1 Luke 2. 51.</note> they occupy the room, and be bound to the ſame truſt, of their natural Parents.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What be the duties of Honour that natural Parents do owe unto their children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Carefully <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal: 127. 4 5. 1 Tim: 5. 8 Judg. 13. 3, 4 Mat: 2. 13, 14 Gen: 21. 7. &amp; 17, 18</note> to endeavour that they may both live, &amp; live well: and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:191876:38"/> that in order therunto, they may be<note place="margin">Mat: 19. 13, 1 Tim: 5. 10. Ephe: 6. 4 Pro: 29. 15 &amp; 22. 6 2 Tim: 1. 5 Pro: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22. Deut: 6. 7 Job 1 5. 1 Sam: 1. 21</note> both well educated by good nurſery, and nurture, and well provided for. 1 <hi>Tim: 3. 4 Gen: 24. 3. 2 Cor:</hi> 12. 14.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Honour, required of Servants towards their Maſters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beſides that <note n="s" place="margin">1 Tim: 6. 1 Mal: 1. 6. Eph 6. 5, 7. Col: 3. 22, 23. Mat: 8 9 1 Pet: 2. 18 Tit: 2. 10.</note> Reverence (belonging to all inferiours) due ſervice and ſubjection, with all faithfulnes &amp; thankfulnes. <hi>Gen: 31. 40. Mat:</hi> 25. 29.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the duty of Masters to their ſervants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As to <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal: 101. 6. Pſal: 15. 4. Pro: 12. 10 Deut. 24. 14, 15. Col: 4. 1 Mat: 8. 5, 6 Exod: 20. 10 Gen: 18. 19 Joſh: 24. 25</note> chooſe (as neer as may be) ſuch as are vertuouſly and piouſly educated, or diſpoſed: So to uſe them chriſtian-like, doing to them that which is equal, and being helpfull to them for their good, in matters ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual &amp; temporal, to their ability.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Honour, we do owe unto our Magiſtrates?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All under their <note n="u" place="margin">Rom: 13. 1. Eccl. 10. 20 Pſal: 82. 1, 6 Acts 26. 25 2 Sam 9. 6, 9 Acts 24. 10 1 Kin: 1. 23, 24. 1 Sam. 22 14. 2 Sam: 24 3. Eſt: 2. 21, 22. 1 Pet: 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. Tit: 3. 1.</note> Authority do owe them the Honour of Revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fidelity, ſubjection &amp; thankfulnes, &amp; prayer for them, &amp; withall ſuch as are concerned in their choiſe, to nominate and elect ſuch, as be Able men, Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God, men of Truth, and hating
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:191876:38"/> Coveteouſnes. <hi>Rom: 13. 6. 1 Pet:</hi> 2. 19.<note place="margin">Exod: 18. 21</note> 
                  <hi>Mat: 17. 22. 1 Tim: 2. 2. Pſal.</hi> 21. 24.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat bee the duties which Magiſtrates owe to their ſubjects?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To <note n="w" place="margin">1 Tim: 2. 2 Eſay 49. 23 Rom: 13, 3, 4 Pſal: 122. 9 Deut: 17. 18, 19. Pſal: 102. 12. Deut: 17. 2</note> improve their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as thoſe that be under them, may lead a quiet and peacable life, in all godlines &amp; honeſty. 2 <hi>Chron: 19. 3, 8, 9. &amp; 31 20. Neh: 13. 10, 28. Job 30. 5, 6. &amp; 20. 13, 14. Eſa. 32. 2. Eſ.</hi> 22. 21</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the Mutual dutyes which Miniſters &amp; people do owe each to other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Inward <note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim: 6. 11 &amp; 4. 12. 2 Cor: 12. 15 Gal: 4. 19 2 Joh 1. &amp; 4 1 Theſ: 5. 13 Gal: 4. 14, 15 1 Theſ: 1. 2. Heb: 13. 18.</note> dear Love and Affection towards each other, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent &amp; earneſt prayer each for other. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 51 7. with 1 <hi>Cor: 13. 4, 5. Col:</hi> 1. 3</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the ſpecial dutyes of People to their Ministers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Finding them to be of God, they are to <note n="z" place="margin">1 John 4. 1 Gal: 4. 14 1 Cor: 4. 1 1 Theſ: 5. 13. &amp; 20. 2 Cor 7. 15. Rom: 10. 15. 2 Cor: 5. 20. Acts 17 11 2 Chron: 20 20. 1 Teſ: 2 13. Mat: 7. 24 1 Tim: 5. 17 1 Cor: 16. 10 &amp; 18. Rom: 1, 6. 4 Gal. 6. 6</note> receive, eſteem &amp; reverence them, to hear them gladly, to hold faſt their good-doctrine, in faith &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and withall to maintain their eſtate with honourable Proviſion, their Credit with due commendation, their Liberty with juſt defence, and their faithfulnes with meet encouragement.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:191876:39"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is farther required, as due to our Church-Officers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As to <note n="a" place="margin">Col. 4. 17. Phil: 2. 9 Rom: 16. 2 Heb: 13. 17</note> ſtirr them up (as need is) to fulfill their Miniſtry: So to refreſh and ſuccour them, and to ſubmit to them in all matters pertaining to their Office, according to God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether is it lawfull to maintein the Miniſtry by a certayin ſet ſtipen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is not only Lawfull, but <note n="b" place="margin">Luke 10. 7 Gen: 47. 22 1 Cor: 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. 15 1 Tim: 5. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18 2 Chron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 31. 6, 10.</note> Safe &amp; honourable for a people ſo to do. <hi>Nehe: 13. 10, 12. Rom:</hi> 13. 8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the duty of the Miniſter to his people?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="c" place="margin">Heb: 5. 4. 2 Cor: 3. 5, 6 Acts 21. 14 Rom: 1. 11 2 Tim: 2. 15 1 Tim: 3. 1 7 Acts 20. 28 1 Tim: 4. 12. Tit: 2. 15 Phil: 2 28 John 5 31 Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: 5. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14 2 Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. 22 Rom: 12. 7 2 Tim: 4. 5. 7 2 Cor: 12. 14 2 Tim: 2. 4.</note> attend the will of God in his being with them, to have them in due eſteem, and to keep himſelf in due eſtimation with them: being an exemplary light unto them, and uſing all diligence in all things, for the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his miniſtry, and the faithfull diſcharge of his truſt amongſt them, as wherof he is to give an account unto his &amp; their Lord, an other day. 1 <hi>Tim 1. 12. 1 Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 4. Heb: 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17. 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 9</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Reaſon here uſed to enforce theſe dutyes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe: 6. 2, 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 11.</note> the Promiſe of a long
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:191876:39"/> and bleſſed life, in a land and place of<note place="margin">Jer: 29. 7.</note> deſires, given us of God.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the Sixt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt not KILL.<note place="margin">Exod: 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Scope of this Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To provide for the ſafety of Mans life, and to that end, all are here<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 21, 26</note> forewarred, to obſerve &amp; ſhun, what ever may tend to the prejudice, of our own, or an others life, both Spiritual &amp; Temporal.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>May murther be committed otherwiſe then in the ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ward act?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, namely as <note n="e" place="margin">Mat: 5. 22.- Mat: 27. 39</note> alſo in heart, geſture, and ſpeeches.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the evills to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded, which in committing of them, would tend to the prejudice of our own, or an others Spiritual life, or would be called Soul-murther?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Principally, The <note n="f" place="margin">Rom: 6. l. Pro: 6. 32 &amp; 8. 36 Rom. 13: 4 Gen: 24. 1, 2 2 Sam: 11. 2. Rom: 2. 4, 5 Heb: 4. 2 Eſay 22. 25 &amp; 33. 7. Jer. 23. 14, 27 1 Cor: 8. 9 Mat: 23. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> leading our ſelves, or others, into any Sin: the ſuffering our ſelves or others, to ly in ſin; or the hindering the free paſſage of the means of Grace, in the peace, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or power of it.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:191876:40"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When may one be ſaid, to bee guilty of ſelf-murther, in reſpect of his own natural life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not only when <note n="g" place="margin">2 Sam: 17. 13. 1 King. 2 22. Mat: 4. 6. 7. Eccl: 5. 19 Pro: 19. 15, Eccl: 4. 5. &amp; 3. 13. 1 Tim: 5. 23. Mat: 9. 12</note> he ſhall either contrive his own death, directly or indirectly, or ſhall careleſsly or deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately expoſe himſelf unto unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry danger: but alſo when he ſhall neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the due means of life, lively-hood, or health.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When may one be ſaid to be guilty of indirect murther, as touching another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When by a <note n="h" place="margin">Deut: 22. 8. Exod: 21. 29 Pro: 24. 11, 12. 2 Sam: 11, 16, 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> careleſs omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or negligent diſcharge of his truſt, his neighbours outward life &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort therof is hazarded.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To ſpeak of murther committed directly againſt our neighbour, What is the murther of the Heart?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> What-ſoever evill is conceived in the <note n="i" place="margin">Mat: 5. 22. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn 3. 15 Acts 7. 9 Pro<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. 18 Pro: 14. 21 &amp; 21 13 &amp; 29. 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y: 3. 15 Pro: 6: 13</note> heart againſt our neighbours life, whereto are referred unjuſt anger and hatred, as the fountaines, Envy, diſdain, contempt, hard-heartednes, feigned freindſhip, cruelty, and ſuch others of the ſame nature; with all their outward ſignes, iſſuing from any theſe fountains.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:191876:40"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is that frame of heart towards others, which this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then requires?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A heart inclining <note n="k" place="margin">Col: 3. 12 Ephe: 4. 32 Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: 11. 29 1 Theſ: 4. 11</note> to kindnes, meeknes, compaſſionatnes, &amp; quietnes. 1 <hi>Cor: 13. 5. Rom:</hi> 12. 15.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When may murther be ſaid to be committed by the Tongue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When <note n="l" place="margin">Pro: 15. 1 &amp; 21. 9 1 Pet: 2. 23 Gal: 4. 29. Pro<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24. 9 Pſal: 109<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17, 18. Pro. 26. 22 &amp; 25. 23 2 Sam: 2. 14</note> ſinful anger, or hatred in the heart, is expreſſed by the tongue, in Brawling, reviling, ſcoffing, curſing, tale-bearing, ſlandering, challenging his neighbour, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What manner of ſpeech is here then required?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That <note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam: 10: 32. Jer: 38. 7, 8. 2 Theſ: 12 4. Pro: 31. 26</note> which is ſo utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to or for another, as tendring his good. <hi>Mat: 10. 12. Ruth 2. 4. Gal.</hi> 6. 1</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the murther, directly committed in act?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="n" place="margin">Gen: 4. 8. 2 Sam: 13. 28 Exod: 22. 10 1 Kin: 21. 19 Exod: 1. 22 Amos 8. 4, 6 Acts 7. 52</note> impairing, or take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the life of ones Neighbour, wittingly, and without a calling.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What dutyes are then required here, as reſpecting his perſon and life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So farr forth, as <note n="o" place="margin">2 Sam: 21. 17. Mat: 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; 42, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> according to his neceſſity, and our calling and ability, to preſerve, protect, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:191876:41"/> his natural life, with the comfort<note place="margin">Heb: 13. 16. Gen: 29. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mat: 25. 35.</note> therof, in the actions of Juſtice, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity &amp; Mercy.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the Seaventh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DULTERY.<note place="margin">Exod: 20, 14</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the main Scope of this Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="p" place="margin">1 Theſ: 4. 4 5. 2 Pet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 11</note> preſcribe to us a Rule, for the preſervation of our own, and our Neighbours chaſtity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Seing alſo, the dutyes enjoyned in order herunto are enforced here, by the contrary evills forbidden; What is that which is here forbidden?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All <note n="q" place="margin">Mat: 15. 19 20.</note> unchaſtity in the heart, or life; whereby our own or an others chaſtity in any ſort is impaired.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Wherein lyes the unchaſtity of the heart?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In <note n="r" place="margin">Gen: 34. 2 Judg: 16 1 Mat: 5. 28 Rom: 1. 24, 25.</note> wanton, filthy, unchaſt thoughts, imaginations, deſires, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, tending to carnal-uncleanes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whrein lyes the the unchaſtity of the life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In <note n="s" place="margin">Gen: 38. 14 16. Jer: 3. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor: 6. 15</note> the abuſe of things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the body, or of the body it ſelf, to uncleanes.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:191876:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherein doth ſuch the abuſes of the body conſiſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the <note n="t" place="margin">Pro: 7. 10. Zeph: 1. 9 1 Tim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 9, 10 Jer: 5. 7, 8 Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea 7. 5, 6. Zech: 16. 49</note> uſing of ought, ordained for bodily refreſhing, comfort or ornament; in a way of lightnes, wantones, exceſs, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntemperancy; whence unclean luſts are occaſionally exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted, or cheriſhed, in our ſelves, or others.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherein lyes the abuſe of the body it ſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor: 15. 33 Col: 3. 8 Pro: 7. 15. &amp; 14. 7 1 John 2. 16 Mat 5 28 Tit: 2. 3 1 Cor: 6. 18 Heb: 13. 4 Lev: 18. 19 Lev: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 23. Rom: 1. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 28.</note> wanton, immodeſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt actings, of any parts of the body, (tending to uncleanes:) as of the whole body, in any unlawfull conjunction.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherin lyes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, that Chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, we ought to preſerve?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In that which is <note n="w" place="margin">Col: 3, 5</note> inward in the heart, conſiſting in a holy free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the motions of unlawfull<note place="margin">1 The: 4. 4, 5</note> concupiſcence there: and in that which is outward of the body, when it is not inſtrumental to the acting thoſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the life.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How may the unchaſtity of the heart and life be avoyded; and the chaſtity of both be preſerved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In general, <note n="x" place="margin">Gen: 39. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> in being in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:191876:42"/> Gods fear, in delighting our ſoules in<note place="margin">Pſal: 119. 9. Pro: 2. 10, 16 1 Tim: 2. 9 Epheſ 5. 3, 4 Pro: 23. 30, 33. 1 Tim: 5. 13.</note> God, in his word, in his ordinances, &amp; wayes: In the exerciſe of modeſty, &amp; ſhamefaſtnes, of temperance, and ſobriety, and of diligence &amp; painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in the dutyes of our general and particular calling.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How may this Chaſtity be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, by perſons in a ſingle est<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such not having the gift of<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1 Tim: 5. 11 14. 1 Cor: 7. 2 &amp; 9. 39.</note> continency, (the former meanes not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayling) are to ſeek, or accept accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God, the benefit of Marriage.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How by thoſe in married eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By a <note n="z" place="margin">Ephe: 5. 28 29. Pro: 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1 Pet: 3. 7 1 Cor: 7. 5. 10, 12. 13 Pro: 31. 11.</note> mutual affecting each the other, with a true Conjugal-love: and doing what ought to be done, for the preſervation &amp; encreaſe of the ſaid love, ſtudiouſly avoiding the contrary.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the eight Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt not STEAL.<note place="margin">Exod: 20. 15</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Scope of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To preſcribe a Rule, for the preventing of any unjuſt alienation of our own, or an others Goods.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>To what end may this be?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:191876:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That each one <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 28. 11 Num: 16. 32 Exod: 22. 7, 8 Mat: 20. 15 Gen: 9. 11 Num: 27. 4. wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h 7. 11</note> may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy peacefully, and without diſturbance his own juſt Rights &amp; proprieties in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of any theſe outward good things</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe evills, which croſse the Scope of this Commandement, as it provides for the ſecuring our own right</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal: 78. 30 Pro: 6. 1, 2. Eccl. 10. 18. John 6. 12. Eccl: 6. 1, 2 2 Kings 8. 3.</note> inordinate deſires, and luſtings of the heart after outward things, Raſh ſpeeches, tending to ones own outward detriment; Idlenes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftines, nigardlynes, with the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of any due means for the preſerving or recovering, ones own right.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What? as the ſame provides for the ſecuring anothers right?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whatſoeuer <note n="c" place="margin">Hab: 2. 9, 10, 11. Pro: 1. 11. &amp; 20. 14. Tit: 2. 10 Pro: 28. 24. Mal: 3. 8. Pro: 10. 2. Mic: 7 3. Pro: 11. 26. Amos 8. 6. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o: 22. 28.</note> inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or outward actions, or ſpeeches, do naturally tend to the prejudice of the outward right of another, or others: whether any family, Church, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale joyntly, or any particular perſon, or perſons ſeveredly.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many wayes may a perſon be wronged by another in his eſtate, under a pretence of doing him right?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So many wayes, as <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam: 18. 17, 25.</note> any the diſtinct Rules reſpectively referring to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:191876:43"/> the differing contracts of this life, are any way croſsed.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How are theſe Rules ſquared?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though <note n="e" place="margin">Gal: 5. 13. Eph: 4. 2. &amp; 5, 2. Rom: 13. 10.</note> differingly, as reſpecting their differing caſes, yet all of them after the Analogy of that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule of Love.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that general Rule of Love?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To <note n="f" place="margin">Mat: 19. 19. Mark 12. 21 Phil: 2. 4, 1 Cor: 13. 5, 6. 1 Cor: 10. 33.</note> Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, and ſo to ſeek his good with thine own.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whence is it that theſe Rules are oft broken under ſuch a pretence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Through the <note n="g" place="margin">1 Theſ: 4, 6 Pro: 20. 17. Pro: 26. 24. Jer: 17. 9.</note> manifold wiles framed in the corrupt mind of man, to ſerve himſelf by.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How many wayes may one be wronged of his right, without all colour of right?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When <note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 10, 30 1 Sam: 2. 16. Exod: 22. 1 Tit: 2. 10 Pro: 28. 24 Deut: 19. 14 Gen: 26. 14, 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eu: 22. 1, 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>v: 6. 2, 4 2 Theſ: 3. 11 Pſal: 50: 18 Pro: 29: 24</note> that which is his, is unjuſtly taken away, either by force, in an open violent way, as by robbery, or ſuch other like violent practiſes of miſcheif: or elſe in a ſecret way; as by pilfering, or any encroaching practiſe or otherwiſe by fraud, as by couſonage concealment, gaming, or by any other crafty &amp; unwarrantable artifice, either
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:191876:43"/> for the procuring, or detaining ought from the right owner.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Root of all this manner of evill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Covetouſnes, <note n="i" place="margin">1 Tim: 6. 9, 10. Mat. 6. 34 Pro: 27. 20. &amp; 28. 20, 22.</note> attended with diſtruſtfulnes of Gods Providence.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What vertues are required to be exerciſed on the contrary part?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Honeſt <note n="k" place="margin">Eph: 4. 28 Pro: 6. 1, 6, 8. &amp; 21. 20. &amp; 27. 23. John 6. 12. Pro: 6. 3. &amp; 30. 9.</note> frugality, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, &amp; equity. 1 <hi>Tim: 6. 17. Lev.</hi> 6. 2</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou ſhalt not bear FALSE<note place="margin">Exod: 20. 10</note> WITNES againſt thy Neighbour.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Scope of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By prohibiting any kind of <note n="l" place="margin">Zeph: 3. 13</note> falſe Teſtimony, tending to our own, or an others hurt, in any the aforeſaid reſpects; to inferr a ſtanding Rule, for the obſervation of Truth &amp; fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in all our witnes bearing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When is a man ſaid to give a falſe Teſtimony againſt himſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When he ſhall either <note n="m" place="margin">Pro: 13. 17 Rev: 3 17. Pſal: 31. 22. Pro: 23. 14. 2 Sam: 1. 16. 2 King: 5. 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pro: 30. 20 Pro: 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> over value, or under-value himſelf to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in his own heart; or ſhall expreſs the ſame to others, by ſpeech or geſture
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:191876:44"/> in any way of boaſting or debaſing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing or accuſing himſelf beſides Rule.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When may he be ſaid to receive a falſe Teſtimony, concerning himſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When <note n="n" place="margin">Acts 12. 22 23. Pſal: 7. 3, 4, 5</note> he ſhall hearken to ſuch as either flatter him, or falſly do accuſe him.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But is there any other way, by which this Commandement is broken, by bearing falſe witnes to our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes aſſuredly, as <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal: 14. 1. Job 22. 13. Pſal: 50. 21. 2 Pet: 3. 4. Jer: 43. 2.</note> if any one ſhall give or receive to himſelf, a falſe teſtimony concerning God, his Truth Will or wayes; or concerning man alive or dead.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then required, to bear witneſs truely touching our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. To <note n="p" place="margin">Rom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12. 3. Tit: 2. 6. 1 Pet: 5. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> judg of our ſelves, according to ſobriety.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <note n="q" place="margin">Pro: 27. 2. John 21. 20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> ſpeak of our ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to modeſty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To <note n="r" place="margin">Mat: 23. 27 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8 Pro: 27. 6.</note> lead our lives according to ſincerity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may a perſon (whether a publick or private perſon) be ſaid to bear falſe witneſs againſt an other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By <note n="s" place="margin">1 Tim: 5. 4 Mat: 11. 1. Sam: 1. 13. Acts 2. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sam: 17. 28 Rom: 14. 4.</note> evill ſurmiſes, raſh judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſdain, or unjuſt contempt, and by falſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:191876:44"/> admiration, conceived in the heart, and<note place="margin">1 Chr: 15. 29. Pro: 11. 12. Pſal: 22. 7 Jude 16. 1 Cor: 3. 4 Eſter 4. 14. Gen: 31. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> uttered in the ſpeech or geſture; or by the neglect of appearing in a good cauſe, or ſpeaking, or acting for it when called to it.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When, or in what caſe is this Commandement broken in, or by an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly-publick-Civil-Aſſembly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When any <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal: 94. 20. 1 Tim: 2. 2. Rom: 13. 4. Dan: 6. 9. 1 Kin: 15. 14 2 King: 12. 3 1 King: 12. 28, 30.</note> Political-Law is attempted or made, as reacheth not, but croſseth the great end, namely the conſerving, or promoting the publick peace, and quiet of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, in all godlines &amp; honeſty.</p>
               <p>2. When in <note n="u" place="margin">Exod: 23 6, 9. Ezra 4. 19. 1 Kin: 21. 10 Rom: 13. 2 Eſther 3. 8 Dan: 5. 1. Pſal: 94. 21. Acts 24. 2, 6 Deut: 19. 16, 19. Acts 25. 7</note> Publick places of Judicature (notwithſtanding wholſome Lawes) Judgment is perverted, Records are unfaithfully reported, or preſerved, unneceſſary ſuits are managed, falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments are forged, falſe witneſſes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned, untrue or uncertain accuſations preferred, juſt uccuſations receded from a juſt ſentence rejected, a good cauſe calumniated, or betrayed, or a raſh or falſe teſtimony exhibited.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When out of places of Judicature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> When <note n="w" place="margin">Judg</note> an unjuſt Law or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhall, or a juſt ſhall not be executed</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:191876:45"/>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is there any danger of the beeach of this Commandement, by falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnes bearing publickly, in our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſemblyes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, manifold wayes; For<note place="margin">
                     <hi>x</hi> Rev: 2. 9. 1 Pet: 5. 3. 1 Cor. 5. 2, 6. Gal. 3. 1. 3, 4 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh: 9, 10. Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 5. 3, 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> beſides what ſuch do, who either falſly aſſume to themſelves, the name of a Church, or do uſurp an exorbitant Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the Lords heritage: Falſe-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes may be born, either by a Church joyntly, or by an Officer, or member in particular.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But may not a falſe witnes bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be in a more ſecret way conſidered?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, As when by our Elections or Proxies, the more <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal: 12. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>: 27. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>e: 6 6, 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>d: 23. 1.</note> worthy ſhall be ſet by, and the unworthy prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: when infamous &amp; defamatory Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells are ſecretly ſpread; or publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famatory rumours raiſed or augmented.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may a man be ſaid to bear falſe witnes privatly againſt his neighbour</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By either <note n="z" place="margin">Pro: 14. 24 Deut: 28. 24</note> an unworthy and untrue commending, or an unjuſt condemning of him behind his back, to a ſingle perſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By [<hi>a</hi>] receiving ſuch a falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.<note place="margin">Pro: 17. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al: 15. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:191876:45"/>3. By <note n="b" place="margin">Ephe: 4. 15. Pſal: 6. 5. 1 Sam: 19. 13</note> aſſerting ought either expreſly, or by way of equivocation; contrary to the preſent trueth of the thing. <hi>John 8. 44. Mat:</hi> 26. 61.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By <note n="c" place="margin">Pro: 25. 14. 2 King: 18. 21.</note> promiſing ought to be done afterward, which either is not intended at the time, or is out of the power of the promiſer. As appears in unfaithfull, deceitfull, or unadviſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is then required of us here?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> To <note n="d" place="margin">Pro: 31<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9 Pſal: 15. 2. 3 John<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1 King. 22. 7</note> judg righteouſly, to ſpeak truely, and to deal faithfully.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the tenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not COVET &amp;c:<note place="margin">Exod: 20. 17</note>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat is the Scope of this Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To <note n="e" place="margin">Pro: 4. 23. &amp; 16 32. Pſal: 119. 36. James 3. 8.</note> preſcribe a Rule, for the right ordering of our hearts, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the very firſt motions &amp; deſires therof, in all thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns our Neighbour, or our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As well the <note n="f" place="margin">Rom: 3. 23. 2 Cor: 3. 5 Rom: 7. 18 Jer: 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> barrenes, or emptines of the heart &amp; mind, of any ſuch motions, thoughts, or deſires, as tend to our own, or our Neighbours
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:191876:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> good: as the preſence of inordinate<note place="margin">Rom: 7. 21 Mat: 15. 19 Rom: 7. 5 Col: 3. 5 Gen: 6: 51 Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: 1. 18 Pſal: 131. 2</note> motions, and evill deſires tending to the contrary; and diſcontent at our preſent condition attending the ſame.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is then here required?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A <note n="g" place="margin">Pro: 16. 32 Heb: 13. 5 1 Tim: 6: 8 Mat: 6. 13 2 Cor: 10. 5. Ephe: 5. 9 Phil: 1: 9.</note> well ordered frame of the heart, quietly contenting it ſelf with the preſent portion or condition meaſured out by God unto us: timely reſiſting &amp; ſuppreſſing, the motions, and temptations of the Divel, world &amp; fleſh; and richly abounding with good motions, thoughts &amp; deſires, as in reſpect as well to our Neighbour, as to our Selves.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Some in the body of the page, As, <hi>p. 45. l. 2. read</hi> and of the Steward. <hi>p. 47. l. 20. for iniciating ſeal read</hi> inicial, or iniciation ſeal. <hi>p. 51. l. 16. for gave, read</hi> immediatly gave &amp; uttered as his will. <hi>p. 79. l. 1. r.</hi> abuſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things of rhe body. Some in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> margent As, <hi>p. 9. l. 21. r.</hi> Luke 7. <hi>l. 25. l.</hi> Rom: 5. <hi>p. 11. l. 12 r.</hi> Hoſ: 1. 9, 10. <hi>p. 13. l. 24. r.</hi> Pſal: 119. 49. <hi>p. 23. l. 1 r.</hi> Mat: 13. <hi>p. 24. l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12: r.</hi> Pſal: 140. <hi>p. 25. l. 18. read</hi> Jer: 6. <hi>p: 26: l. 3. r:</hi> Pet: 4: <hi>p. 33. l. 9: r.</hi> Pro: 30 <hi>p. 40. l. 6. r.</hi> Eph: 1. <hi>p: 48. l. 12. r</hi> Ezek: 4: <hi>p: 50. l: 15 r:</hi> Gal: 2: <hi>p: 52. l: 4. r:</hi> Eſay 45. <hi>p: 55. l: 13. r:</hi> 2 Pet 1. <hi>p: 69. l: 2. r:</hi> Eccl: 10. 2. <hi>p: 70. l: 25. r: 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13. p. 78. l: 11. r:</hi> 1 Pet: <hi>l: 27. r:</hi> Jer: 5.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:46"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191876:47"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
